<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="clinton_130168"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title><seg type="short-title">The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</seg>, an electronic
	    edition. Edited with an introduction by Kate McPherson</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Lincoln, Elizabeth Clinton, Countess of</reg><orig>Elizabeth Knevet Clinton</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Kate McPherson</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>160kb</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability><p xml:id="clinton_1301">1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Emory Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>1996</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/17bfb</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Clinton, Elizabeth Knevet. The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie: A Critical Edition.  Ed. Kate McPherson.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="clinton_1302">This text is produced in conjunction with the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p><p xml:id="clinton_1303">We have used the "orig" tag to designate regularized spellings of words for searching purposes.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Early Modern through the 18th Century</rs><rs type="language">English</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs><rs type="form">Edited</rs><rs type="genre">Prose</rs><rs type="geography">Great Britain</rs><date>1600-1699</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list><item>Breastfeeding--Early works to 1800.</item><item>Motherhood.</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="clinton_130167"><body xml:id="clinton_130166"><div xml:id="clinton_000" type="critical_introduction"><div xml:id="clinton_001" type="Introduction"><head><title>The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>: A Critical Edition</head><docAuthor>McPherson, Kate</docAuthor><div xml:id="clinton_002" type="Contents"><head><seg type="short-title">Contents</seg> for <title>The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>: A Critical Edition</head><p xml:id="clinton_1304"><hi rend="bold">Introduction</hi>:</p><p xml:id="clinton_1305">I. "What a racket do Authors make about this": The Debate Over Maternal Breastfeeding in Early Modern England . . . ii</p><p xml:id="clinton_1306">II. "And to be short, the mothers <choice><reg>milk</reg><sic>milke</sic></choice> is most wholesome for the <choice><reg>child</reg><sic>childe</sic></choice>   ":  Medical Texts and Maternal Breastfeeding . . . iii</p><p xml:id="clinton_1307">III. "Sure if their breasts be <choice><reg>dry</reg><sic>drie</sic></choice> . . . they should fast and pray together": Breastfeeding and Moral Advice Tracts in Early Modern England . . . vii</p><p xml:id="clinton_1308">IV. "We were sensible of the neglect of duty in not having nursed her": Personal Testimony about Breastfeeding . . . xi</p><p xml:id="clinton_1309">V.  Joining the Discourse: The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie . . . xv</p><p xml:id="clinton_13010">VI. A Note on Editorial Practice . . . xxiii</p><p xml:id="clinton_13011">VII. Biographical Essay: Elizabeth Knevet Clinton . . . xxiv</p><p xml:id="clinton_13012"><hi rend="bold">The Text</hi>:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13013"><title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> . . . 1</p></div><pb xml:id="clinton_13014" n="ii"/><div xml:id="clinton_003" n="1" type="Section"><head><seg type="short-title">Introduction</seg><lb/>
I.<lb/>
"What a racket do Authors make about this": The Debate Over 
Maternal Breastfeeding in Early Modern England</head><p xml:id="clinton_13015">In the seventeenth century, the vast majority of noble- and gentlewomen employed commoners as wet nurses.  This practice, in combination with rising religious conservatism, incited a socio-religious controversy about breastfeeding.  Doctors, theologians, midwives, and one outspoken noblewomen all joined this often rancorous debate.  That noblewoman, Elizabeth Clinton, the Dowager Countess of Lincoln, penned the 1622 pamphlet, <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, which is the only female-authored text devoted entirely to the subject.  Problematically, medical texts promoted maternal breastfeeding, yet simultaneously offered readers extensive directions for choosing a wet nurse.  Moralistic literature, like <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, countered this tacit endorsement of wet nursing by exhorting readers about the godliness of mothers nursing their own children.  Nicholas Culpepper, an herbalist and physician, mocks the controversy:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13016"><q>What a racket do Authors make about this!  What thwarting and contradicting, not of others only but of themselves!  What reasons do they bring, why a woman must needs nurse her own child?  Some extorted from Divinity. . . Some they have haled it head and shoulders from reason.  The Mothers milk is most convenient for the child because the child participates of her Nature. . . . Or else because the woman cannot love her child, except she give it suck her own self, which if she <choice><reg>do</reg><sic>doe</sic></choice>  not more inhumane beast she.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro1">1</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro1" n="1">Nicholas Culpepper, <title>Culpepper's Midwife Enlarged</title> (London, 1684), L4v.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13017">Culpepper mentions the primary reasons maternal breastfeeding was encouraged-religious duty, natural law, and maternal obligation--but he also perceives the selective use of these justifications.  Although Clinton was not the first Puritan to preach about breastfeeding, she was the first woman to <hi rend="italic">publish</hi> her views on the topic, providing a rare example of a woman contributing to the predominantly male discourse about proper maternal behavior.</p></div><pb xml:id="clinton_13018" n="iii"/><div xml:id="clinton_004" n="2" type="Section"><head>II.<lb/>
"And to be short, the mothers 
              
              <choice><reg>milk</reg><sic>milke</sic></choice>   
              
              is most wholesome for the <choice><reg>child</reg><sic>childe</sic></choice>":  
<seg type="short-title">Medical Texts and Maternal Breastfeeding</seg></head><p xml:id="clinton_13019">Almost without exception, midwifery manuals published and written in the seventeenth century recommend that all mothers breastfeed their own children.  The  influential French physician Ambrose Paré, his student Jacques Guillemeau, and various English authors including Nicholas Culpepper and Jane Sharp all strongly recommend maternal breastfeeding.  A 1540 manual, <title>The Birth of Man-Kinde</title>, which was reprinted numerous times in the seventeenth century, includes the medical reasons why mothers should nurse: "it shall be best that the mother give her 
              
              <choice><reg>child</reg><sic>childe</sic></choice><choice><reg>suck</reg><sic>sucke</sic></choice><choice><reg>herself</reg><sic>herselfe</sic></choice><choice><reg>milk</reg><sic>milke</sic></choice>   
              
              is more convenient and agreeable to the infant then any other 
              
              <choice><reg>woman's</reg><sic>womans</sic></choice>   
              
               &amp; more doth nourish it, for because that in the mothers belly it was wont to the same &amp; fed with it." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro2">2</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro2" n="2">Eucharius Rosselin, <title>The Birth of Man-Kinde: otherwise named the Womans Booke</title>. Trans. Thomas Raynald (London: 1616), L6v-L7r.  Rosselin's text, originally published in Latin in 1540, was one of the early modern period's most popular obstetrical texts, going through numerous editions between 1540 and 1700.</note>  Physicians at this time believed that breast milk was a sort of refined blood, and since the child was used to the mother's blood, it would also thrive more on her milk. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro3">3</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro3" n="3">See Valerie Fildes, <title>Breasts, Bottles, and Babies: A History of Infant Feeding</title> (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1986), 99-116.   Gail Kern Paster also discusses the importance of this theory in <title>The Body Embarrassed: Drama and the Disciplines of Shame in Early Modern England</title> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1993), 198-208.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13020">Despite theories about the beneficial medical
	       effects of breastfeeding, physicians more often
	       discussed what they believed were the emotional effects
	       of using a wet nurse: problems with the development of
	       the child's character and the consequences of wet
	       nursing on the mother-infant relationship.
	       Consequently, these commentaries frequently stray from
	       the realm of medical advice into moral instruction.
	       Ambrose Paré, for instance, makes the following heated
	       comment:</p><pb xml:id="clinton_13021" n="iv"/><p xml:id="clinton_13022"><q>And moreover, mothers ought to nurse their  
                
                <choice><reg>own</reg><sic>owne</sic></choice>   
                
                children, because of the most part, they are 
                
                <choice><reg>far</reg><sic>farre</sic></choice><choice><reg>careful</reg><sic>carefull</sic></choice>   
                
                 in bringing up and attending their children than hired and mercenary nurses, which  
                
                <choice><reg>do</reg><sic>doe</sic></choice>   
                
                 not  
                
                <choice><reg>so</reg><sic>soe</sic></choice>   
                
                 much regard the infant as the  
                
                <choice><reg>gain</reg><sic>gaine</sic></choice>   
                
                 they shall have by keeping it.  Those that  
                
                <choice><reg>do</reg><sic>doe</sic></choice>   
                
                 not nurse their 
                
                <choice><reg>own</reg><sic>owne</sic></choice>
                
                children, cannot rightly be termed mothers: for they  
                
                <choice><reg>do</reg><sic>doe</sic></choice>   
                
                not absolutely  
                
                <choice><reg>perform</reg><sic>performe</sic></choice>   
                
                 the duty of a mother unto the child. . . . For this is a  
                
                <choice><reg>certain</reg><sic>certaine</sic></choice>   
                
                 unnatural, imperfect and 
                
                <choice><reg>half</reg><sic>halfe</sic></choice><choice><reg>kind</reg><sic>kinde</sic></choice>   
                
                 of a mothers  
                
                <choice><reg>duty</reg><sic>dutie</sic></choice>   
                
               , to 
                
                <choice><reg>bear</reg><sic>beare</sic></choice>  
                
                 a  
                
                <choice><reg>child</reg><sic>childe</sic></choice>   
                
                 and presently to abandon or put it away as if it were forsaken.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro4">4</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro4" n="4">Ambrose Paré, <title>The Workes of that famous Chirurgeon Ambrose Pare, translated out of Latine and compared with the French</title>.  Trans. Thomas Gornson (London, 1634), Gggg4r-Gggg4v.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13023">Paré's rhetoric, with its emphasis on the unnaturalness of a non-nursing mother, seems designed to shame women into breastfeeding.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13024">Yet despite this strong endorsement of maternal breastfeeding, Paré details the characteristics and behavior of a good wet nurse:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13025"><q>Both in eating, drinking, sleeping, watching, exercising, and resting, the nurses diet must be divers, according to the nature of the child. . . . let her live in pure and <choice><reg>clear</reg><orig>cleere</orig></choice> air, let her abstain from all spices, and all salted and spiced <choice><reg>meats</reg><orig>meates</orig></choice>, and all <choice><reg>sharp</reg><orig>sharpe</orig></choice> things, wine, especially that which is not allayed or mixed with water, and <choice><reg>carnal</reg><orig>carnall</orig></choice> copulations; let her <choice><reg>avoid</reg><orig>avoyd</orig></choice> all perturbations of the mind, but anger especially. . . .</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro5">5</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro5" n="5">Ibid., Gggg5v.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13026">In truth, his text devotes more space to choosing a wet nurse than to encouraging maternal breastfeeding.  He moralizes at length about the virtues of nursing mothers but he also (perhaps realistically) acknowledges that religious, economic, and social factors resulted in many women using wet nurses for their children.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13027">Jacques Guillemeau likewise discusses physical and social factors that justify employing a wet nurse, although he also asserts that maternal devotion should lead a woman to breastfeed her own child:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13029"><q>Though it were fit that every mother doth nurse her own child: because her <choice><reg>milk</reg><orig>Milke</orig></choice>, which is nothing but blood whitened (of which he was made. . .) will always be more natural and familiar to him, than that of a stranger: and also by nursing him herself she shall be wholly accounted his mother, yet since they may be hindered by <choice><reg>sickness</reg><orig>sicknesse</orig></choice>, or for that they are too weak and tender, or else because their 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13028" n="v"/>
Husbands will not suffer them, therefore I say, it will very necessary to seek out another Nurse. . . .</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro6">6</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro6" n="6">Jacques Guillemeau, <title>Childbirth, or the Happie Delivery of Women</title> (London, 1635), Kk4r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13030">Guillemeau moves skillfully from endorsing maternal
	       breastfeeding to defending wet nursing: the mother may
	       be too weak to nurse, but she may also be prevented by
	       her husband (who will not "suffer" or endure her
	       nursing because of the assumed avoidance of sexual
	       intercourse by nursing women).<ref target="#clinton.010.intro7">7</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro7" n="7">Valerie Fildes notes that ancient beliefs derived from Galenic medicine, which strongly recommended that all nursing women avoid sexual relations.  By the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, "this injunction appears to have been applied only to wet nurses employed in the child's home."  She believes that the taboo was rarely acknowledged by "British parents, or by medical and theological authors writing in English." See <title>Breasts, Bottles, and Babies</title>, 104.  Elizabeth Clinton also glances at this taboo when she observes that her desire to nurse was "overruled by <choice><reg>another's</reg><sic>anothers</sic></choice> authority".  See <title>The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> D1v.</note>  Guillemeau accepts that social pressures sometimes outweigh morality, but his equivocation would have left parents with no authority on which to depend.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13031">This apparent conflict between cultural practices and medical/moral recommendations survived the Restoration, resurfacing in Jane Sharp's <title>Midwives Book, Or the Whole Art of Midwifery Discovered</title>, which was the first female-authored book of midwifery advice and, besides <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, the only other woman's published opinion about breastfeeding in the seventeenth century. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro8">8</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro8" n="8">Jane Sharp, <title>The Midwives Book</title> (London, 1671).  I quote from the Brown University Women Writer's Project Draft in Process.  Elaine Hobby has recently prepared a modern edition of <title>The Midwives Book</title> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1999).</note>   Sharp, however, differs distinctly from Clinton and more closely resembles (although she does not mimic) male writers of midwifery texts.  Sharp's is a medical, not a moral, treatise and thus she includes only a brief discussion of the necessity of maternal breastfeeding, devoting a greater portion of her chapter, "Directions for Nurses," to choosing a wet nurse and treating diseases of the breast.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13032">However, Sharp also displays her awareness of the controversy over breastfeeding:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13034"><q>The dispute about Nurses, who are fit for it, and who are not, is much handled by Physicians; and there be some that will <choice><reg>tie</reg><orig>tye</orig></choice> every woman to Nurse her own child because Sarah, the wife of so great a man as Abraham was, nursed Isaac:  And indeed if there be no other obstacle the Argument may carry some weight with it; for doubtless the mothers milk is commonly best agreeing with the child; and if the mother do not Nurse her own child, it is a question whether she will ever love 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13033" n="vi"/>
it so well as she that proves the Nurse to it as well as Mother: and without doubt the child will be much alienated in his affections by sucking of strange milk. . . .</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro9">9</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro9" n="9">Ibid., 145.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13035">Sharp equivocates about women's moral duty to breastfeed.  She carefully hedges the religious argument, for instance, by saying the example of Sarah "may carry some weight," but only "if there be no other obstacle."  Although she employs Biblical exempla, Sharp focuses her argument on the social (rather than the religious) ramifications of wet nursing.  Sharp equivocation may result from her awareness that most privileged women believed breastfeeding limited mobility, lowered fertility, and raised the objections of their spouses and peers. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro10">10</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro10" n="10">For instance, Lady Anne Newdigate incurred the ire of both her father and the godfather to her child when she chose to nurse her baby in 1598; the godfather, Sir William Knollys, admitted that "play[ing] the nurse. . .argueth great love, but it breedeth much trouble to yourself and it would more grieve you if sucking your own milk it should miscarry, children being subject to many casualties." Knollys nods toward Newdigate's devotion to maternal duty, but intimates that she risks too much emotionally (and perhaps socially) by performing her "great love."  This incident is reported in David Cressy's <title>Birth, Marriage, and Death: Ritual, Religion and the Life-Cycle in Tudor and Stuart England</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1997), 90-91.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13036">Yet Sharp complicates her position on maternal breastfeeding by criticizing wealthy women who employ wet nurses unnecessarily.  She comments:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13037"><q>The usual way for rich people is to put forth their child to nurse, but that is a remedy that needs a remedy, if it might be had: because it <orig reg="changes">changeth</orig> the natural disposition of the child and oftentimes exposes the infant to many hazards, if great care is not taken in the choice of the nurse.</q></p><p xml:id="clinton_13038"><q>There are not many Women that want milk to suckle their own children. . . but multitudes pretend <choice><reg/><orig/></choice><orig reg="weakness">weakeness</orig> when they have not cause for it, because they have not so much love for their own, as Dumb creatures have. . . .</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro11">11</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro11" n="11">Sharp, <title>The Midwives Book</title>, 145 and 148.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13039">Clearly, Sharp believes women are morally obligated to breastfeed whenever they are able. </p><p xml:id="clinton_13041">But Sharp tempers her criticism when she notes that the hazards to the wet-nursed child occur only "if great care is not taken in the choice of a nurse." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro12">12</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro12" n="12">Ibid., 145.</note>  Since she gives extensive directions for choosing a nurse, presumably she believes that locating a qualified wet nurse is indeed possible.  Sharp also wavers between using women's fear of losing their child's affections by its "sucking of strange milk" and compassion for the difficulties of childbirth and nursing.  
<pb xml:id="clinton_13040" n="vii"/>
Her views, more flexible than those in many other medical texts from the period, reveal that she acknowledged the conflicted status of maternal breastfeeding, and strove to provide constructive advice to families on both sides of the divide.  Not surprisingly, no such flexibility can be found in the numerous religious and moralistic tracts of the period which frequently sought to prescribe maternal behavior.</p></div><div xml:id="clinton_005" n="3" type="Section"><head>III.<lb/>
              "Sure if their breasts be <choice><reg>dry</reg><orig>drie</orig></choice>. . . they should fast and pray together":
<seg type="short-title">Breastfeeding and Moral Advice Tracts</seg> in Early Modern England</head><p xml:id="clinton_13042">Like Elizabeth Clinton, other seventeenth-century moralists used strong moral arguments against wet nursing to fill the void left by equivocating physicians.  Their message was clear: any woman who did not nurse her child defied God's will and endangered her child.  This serious moral condemnation of non-nursing mothers obviously clashed with entrenched custom in many high-ranking families, as well as with the recommendations about nurses prevalent in much medical advice.  In his only sustained commentary on breastfeeding in <title>The Family, Sex, and Marriage, 1500-1800</title>, Lawrence Stone attributes the rising concern about maternal breastfeeding to these same Puritan authors:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13043"><q>In the early seventeenth century the most popular and influential Puritan writers on household management, Perkins, Gouge, and Dod and Clever, strongly reinforced the traditional advice of the medical profession, and told mothers to feed their own children.  They used the functional argument that nature had provided women with breasts to supply milk, not to serve as sexually exciting erogenous zones; they used the medical argument that the mother's milk was best; and they used the ancient superstition that by absorbing wet-nurses' milk, babies would also pick up their lower-class, and probably evil, character traits.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro13">13</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro13" n="13">Lawrence Stone, <title>The Family, Sex, and Marriage in England, 1500-1800, Abridged Edition</title>. (New York: Harper Torchbooks, 1979), 270.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13045">Although Stone identifies the many social arguments used by these Puritan writers, he neglects any exploration of the religious motivation for their concern.  These writers appeal to nature, 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13044" n="viii"/>
love, health, and above all Christian duty, to prove that all mothers who are physically able ought to breastfeed their children.  In essence, they use every argument at their disposal to attempt to promote proper maternal conduct in an ideal Christian culture.<ref target="#clinton.010.intro14">14</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro14" n="14">Such didactic texts did not, admittedly, originate in the seventeenth century.  Erasmus' <title>Colloquies or Familiar Discourses</title>, which was initially published in 1522 in a Latin edition, features a fictional dialogue to discourage wet nursing.  See <title>Colloquies. . .Rendered into English by H.M.</title> (London, 1671).  Erasmus employs both moral and emotional arguments to dissuade women from using wet nurses.  His commitment to maternal breast feeding, and the language he uses to express it, are only a shadow of the extreme rhetoric about breast feeding that permeated moral tracts in the seventeenth century. </note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13046">For instance, the 1612 conduct manual John Dod and Roberts Clever's <title>A Godly <choice><reg>form</reg><orig>forme</orig></choice> of Household Government</title> includes breastfeeding as part of  "What the <choice><reg>duty</reg><orig>dutie</orig></choice> of a Wife is toward her Husband."  In addition to citing Biblical examples of wifely silence and submission, the writers address the wife's duty to breastfeed her children in order to "be a helpmeet unto her husband in suckling the child common to them both."<ref target="#clinton.010.intro15">15</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro15" n="15">John Dod and Robert Cleaver, <title>A Godly <choice><reg>form</reg><orig>forme</orig></choice> of Household Government for the Ordering of Private Families</title> (London, 1612), Q2v.</note>  They accuse women who employ wet nurses of being "nice and <choice><reg>unnatural</reg><orig>unnaturall</orig></choice> mothers. . .[who] make themselves but half-mothers, &amp; so break the holy bond of nature."<ref target="#clinton.010.intro16">16</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro16" n="16">Ibid., P5r.</note>  The intensity of their rhetoric peaks when they attack wealthy women who feign a lack of milk:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13047"><q>But whose breasts have this perpetual drought?  Forsoothe it is like the <choice><reg>gout</reg><orig>goute</orig></choice>, no beggars may have it, but citizens or Gentlewomen.  In the ninth chapter of Hosea, <choice><reg>dry</reg><orig>drie</orig></choice> breasts are named for a curse: what lamentable happe have Gentlewomen to light upon this curse more than others?  Sure if their breasts be <choice><reg>dry</reg><orig>drie</orig></choice>, as they say, they should fast and pray together that this curse may be removed from them.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro17">17</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro17" n="17">Ibid., Q2v.  It should be noted that this passage is taken verbatim from Henrie Smith's sermon, <title>A Preparative to Marriage</title> (London, 1591), G8v-H1r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13048">Clearly, Dod and Clever are extremists who want women to abandon an entrenched childrearing practice in favor of their strict interpretation of the Bible.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13050">William Gouge's 1622 volume, <title>Of Domesticall Duties</title>, is similarly unyielding.  Gouge uses many of the same arguments employed by Dod and Clever to encourage godly women to breastfeed their own children.  Published in the same year as <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes</title><pb xml:id="clinton_13049" n="ix"/><title>Nurserie</title>, Gouge's lengthy treatise is a comprehensive discussion of Puritan household management. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro18">18</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro18" n="18">William Gouge, <title>Of Domesticall Duties: Eight Treatises</title> (London, 1622), K3v.</note>  When discussing nursing, he uses the examples of Sarah, Hannah, and Mary to prove that good women always nursed their children.  Part of his idea of goodness is also tied to maternal self-sacrifice.  He carefully stresses that pain and injury do not obviate the woman's duty to her child: "a mother with enduring a little more pain may safely give the child <choice><reg>suck</reg><orig>sucke</orig></choice>.  Many mothers have given their children <choice><reg>suck</reg><orig>sucke</orig></choice> when <choice><reg>blood</reg><orig>bloud</orig></choice> hath <choice><reg>run</reg><orig>runne</orig></choice> by the mouth of the child by reason of sore nipples, and yet both mother and child have done very well."<ref target="#clinton.010.intro19">19</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro19" n="19">Ibid., L3r.</note>  Gouge's graphic depiction of a mother suffering to nurse her child vividly illustrates his rigid standards of maternal behavior.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13051">Gouge also believes, though, that "many husbands will not suffer their wives to nurse their children themselves." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro20">20</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro20" n="20">Ibid., K4v.</note>  Gouge does not, of course, recommend disrupting the patriarchal household order, but he does add that "[t]he <choice><reg>duty</reg><orig>dutie</orig></choice> on a fathers part in this respect is required that he <choice><reg>encourage</reg><orig>incourage</orig></choice> his wife, and <choice><reg>help</reg><orig>helpe</orig></choice> her with all needful things for the performance of this duty." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro21">21</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro21" n="21">Ibid., L1r.</note>  Paternal objections, such as "trouble, disquiet, and <choice><reg>expense</reg><orig>expence</orig></choice> carry little weight with Gouge. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro22">22</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro22" n="22">Ibid.</note>  He strongly censures those husbands who prevent their wives from nursing:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13052"><q>The mothers <choice><reg>pain</reg><orig>paine</orig></choice> is the greatest: it is in comparison but a small thing that father can endure therein.  Their fault therefore must be the greater, if in any way they be an occasion of their <choice><reg>children</reg><orig>childes</orig></choice> putting forth to nurse: which I have the rather noted because husbands for the most part are the cause that their wives not nurse their <choice><reg>own</reg><orig>owne</orig></choice> children. . . . If husbands were willing that their wives should <choice><reg>perform</reg><orig>performe</orig></choice> this <choice><reg>duty</reg><orig>dutie</orig></choice> and would <choice><reg>persuade</reg><orig>purswade</orig></choice> and <choice><reg>encourage</reg><orig>incourage</orig></choice> them thereto, and afford them what <choice><reg>helps</reg><orig>helpes</orig></choice> they could, where one mother now nurseth her <choice><reg>child</reg><orig>childe</orig></choice>, twenty would do it.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro23">23</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro23" n="23">Ibid., L1v.</note></p><pb xml:id="clinton_13053" n="x"/><p xml:id="clinton_13054">Though, Gouge pushes women to nurse their children, he also impels men to support the practice so that both mother and father can perform their "bounden duty."</p><p xml:id="clinton_13055">Like the medical controversy over wet nurses, the Puritan effort promote maternal breastfeeding survived the Restoration.  Reverend Henry Newcome's 1695 <title>The Compleat Mother, Or an Earnest Perswasive to all Mothers (especially those of Rank and Quality) to Nurse their Own Children</title> makes a sustained appeal to end wet nursing.  It is the only seventeenth-century text besides <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> devoted exclusively to the duty of mothers to nurse their own children, and it is similarly directed at women of "Rank and Quality."  Labeling wealthy women who use wet nurses "impious," Newcome makes exceptions only when nursing would endanger either the mother's or the child's health. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro24">24</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro24" n="24"><title>The Compleat Mother, Or an Earnest Perswasive to all Mothers (especially those of Rank and Quality) to Nurse their Own Children</title> (London, 1695), G2r-G5v.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13056">Like most of the other moralistic tracts about breastfeeding, <title>The Compleat Mother</title> argues that wealth and position affect a mother's choice to breastfeed. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro25">25</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro25" n="25">Wealthy women were often singled out as violating codes of proper maternal behavior.  One 1671 midwifery manual includes the following diatribe:<lb/><q>Their own mothers surely (if they are able) both by duty and nature, being the most fit to nurse their own children, which the greatest Ladies may do, with the greatest conveniences, by reason of their plenty of all things; besides, their attendance of servants, who can bring their <choice><reg>nursery</reg><orig>nurseries</orig></choice> to them at all hours, be it day or night, and take them <choice><reg>again</reg><orig>againe</orig></choice>, not to disturb their rest: which also they may intend at their own pleasure.</q><lb/>
The author, James Wolveridge, like most other writers with Puritan leanings--including the Countess of Lincoln--blames the prevalence of wet nursing on the laziness and selfishness of women of quality.  Newcome follows their lead in his attack.  See Wolveridge, <title>Speculum Matricis Or The Expert Midwives Handmaid Catechistically Composed</title> (London, 1671), L5r.</note>   Newcome points out that children of the "Nobility and Gentry" are more likely to be put out to nurse:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13057"><q>The <title>Poor Tenants Child</title> is for the most part nursed in its own Mothers bosom, and cherished by her breasts, whilst the Landlord's heir is <choice><reg>turned</reg><orig>turn'd</orig></choice> out, exiled from his Mothers embraces as soon as from her Womb, and assigned to the Care of some Stranger. . . .Thus the Infants of the best Families are most hardly used, and vast numbers of them undoubtedly destroyed.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro26">26</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro26" n="26">Newcome, <title>The Compleat Mother</title>, B4r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13059">Newcome appeals to two emotional issues here: the aristocratic concern with a successful lineage and mothers' love and fear for their children.  Newcome takes his persuasive task seriously, 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13058" n="xi"/>
moving beyond exhortations of biblical duty and into direct emotional appeals to parents, and to women in particular.  Although <title>The Compleat Mother</title>, and other texts like it promoted maternal breastfeeding across class lines, such polemics had little measurable effect.  Wet nursing continued to be the norm among the higher ranks, as many diaries and memoirs attest.</p></div><div xml:id="clinton_006" n="4" type="Section"><head>IV.<lb/>
"We were sensible of the neglect of duty in not having nursed her": 
<seg type="short-title">Personal Testimony</seg> about Breastfeeding</head><p xml:id="clinton_13061">Against the background of the various medical and moral treatments of nursing discussed above, it is crucial to examine actual representations of breastfeeding experiences in  early modern English families of rank.  Valerie Wayne comments that "early modern mothers were taught that their own salvation depended on nurturing children. . . ." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro27">27</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro27" n="27">Valerie Wayne, "Advice for women from mothers and patriarchs" in <title>Women and Literature in Britain, 1500-1700</title>, ed. Helen Wilcox (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996. 56-79), 62.</note>  Precisely how those children were nurtured (or nursed) can reveal to what extent the ambivalence of doctors and the certainty of moralists affected the use of wet nurses.  Valerie Fildes notes that wet nursing reached its height during this period in England, when mothers from royalty through the lower merchant classes employed wet nurses. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro28">28</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro28" n="28">Valerie Fildes, <title>Wet Nursing: A History from Antiquity to the Present</title> (London: Basil Blackwell, 1988), 79.</note> Other historians, including Dorothy McLaren, argue that it was during this time that the breast became eroticized and thus nursing (which emphasizes the functional rather than the sexual aspect of the breast) was almost wholly shunted onto women of the lower ranks, who were necessarily less concerned with vanity. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro29">29</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro29" n="29">See Dorothy McLaren, "Marital Fertility and Lactation, 1570-1720" in <title>Women in English Society, 1500-1800</title>, ed. Mary Prior (London: Methuen, 1985. 22-53), 27-28.  See also Marilyn Yalom, <title>A History of the Breast</title> (New York: Knopf, 1997).</note> But, as Gail Kern Paster observes, a gentle- or noblewoman's choice was also complicated by issues of conflicting 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13060" n="xii"/>
medical advice, as well as concerns regarding fertility, beauty, and association with a type of economic production. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro30">30</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro30" n="30">See Paster, <title>The Body Embarrassed</title>, 208 for a lucid discussion of these complications.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13062">Personal testimony reveals, not surprisingly, that maternal nursing enjoyed only mixed popularity among the upper ranks in the seventeenth century.  These families, faced with the barrage of moral advice and its conflict with custom in their peer group, frequently acted according to their religious preference, i.e., with nonconformist or Puritan mothers breastfeeding and Anglican mothers employing wet nurses. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro31">31</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro31" n="31">For instance, the nonconformist minister's wife, Jane Josselin, nursed her children unless she was too ill postpartum to do so. (See <title>The Diary of Ralph Josselin</title>, ed. Alan Macfarlane.  London: The British Academy for Oxford University Press, 1976.  50, 112-116).  On the other hand, Lady Mary Verney sends her newborn son to stay with a nurse who "looks like a slattern" and says "if <choice><reg>she</reg><orig>shee</orig></choice> takes the child <choice><reg>she</reg><orig>shee</orig></choice> will have a mighty care of it." (<title>The Memoirs of the Verney Family during the Seventeenth Century</title>, ed. F.P. and M.M. Verney.  London, 1907), 361.)</note>  Paster notes that "the rhetorical energy aroused by the question of maternal breastfeeding also suggests that in social classes that had a degree of personal choice. . . any infant feeding practice was capable of contestation and challenge on a number of grounds." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro32">32</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro32" n="32">Ibid., 198.</note>   The frequency of these challenges and their limited success demonstrates the sporadic effectiveness of expert advice about breastfeeding, and further illustrates that religious efforts to regulate maternity never took firm hold.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13064">For instance, both Lady Elizabeth Egerton, Countess of Bridgewater, and Lady Elizabeth Carey, Viscountess Mordaunt, record long sections regarding pregnancy and childbirth in their writings. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro33">33</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro33" n="33">See <title>True Coppies of <choice><reg>certain</reg><orig>certaine</orig></choice> Loose Papers left by ye Right Honorable Elizabeth, Countess of Bridgewater.  Collected and Transcribed together here since Her Death, Anno Domini 1663</title> (BL Egerton MS 607) for Egerton's meditations on childbearing, and <title>The private diary of Elizabeth, Viscountess Mordaunt</title> (Duncairn, 1856) for Mordaunt's prayers and poems on childbirth.</note>  Each left lengthy prayers, several short poems, and numerous meditations on successful childbirth and infant mortality, demonstrating that they reflected on motherhood and its obligations.  Additionally, both women were pious adherents of the Church of England, and nothing in their diaries indicates any degree of religious dissent.  As energetic as they were about recording other aspects of their maternal experience, neither makes any mention of nursing her 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13063" n="xiii"/>
children, a fact that suggests they, like most gentlewomen, probably hired wet nurses.  For them, the practice was so customary that it passed without notice.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13065">Alice Thornton, a gentlewoman from Yorkshire,<ref target="#clinton.010.intro34">34</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro34" n="34">Thornton, who lived from 1626-1710, was the daughter of Sir Christopher Wandesford, a secretary to the Governor of Ireland.  See <title>The Feminist Companion to Literature in English</title> (ed.  Virginia Blain et al.,  New Haven: Yale University Press, 1990).</note> however, quickly abandoned using a wet nurse when she discovers that the nurse's presence in the family home (rather than in the nurse's village) endangers the baby's life.  Thornton records that her daughter was,</p><p xml:id="clinton_13066"><q>one night delivered from <choice><reg>being</reg><orig>beeing</orig></choice> overlaid by her nurse, who laid in my <choice><reg>dear</reg><orig>deare</orig></choice> mother's chamber a good while.  One night my mother was writing pretty late, and heard my <choice><reg>dear</reg><orig>deare</orig></choice><choice><reg>child</reg><orig>childe</orig></choice> make a <choice><reg>groaning</reg><orig>groaninge</orig></choice><choice><reg>troublesomely</reg><orig>troublsomly</orig></choice>, and <orig reg="stepping">steping</orig> immediately to the nurse's bed side, she saw the nurse fallen <orig reg="asleep">asleepe</orig>, with her breast in the child's mouth; at which, she <orig reg="being">beeing</orig> affrighted, pulled the nurse <orig reg="suddenly">suddainly</orig> from her, and <orig reg="so">soe</orig> preserved my <orig reg="dear">deare</orig><orig reg="child">childe</orig> from <orig reg="being">beeing</orig> smothered.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro35">35</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro35" n="35"><title>The Autobiography of Mrs. Alice Thornton of East Newton, Co, York</title>, ed. Charles Jackson (London: Surtees Society, 1875), 91.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13067">As Thornton's case demonstrates, dangers to wet-nursed children were not merely emphasized by many conduct books for rhetorical purposes.  And, just as moral writers like Gouge or Newcome recommended, Alice Thornton changed her behavior when her next child was born.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13068">The fear inspired by her first child's near fatal overlaying led Thornton to nurse her next child, Betty, although she was very ill after the birth.  She notes, "I recovered my <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, and was overjoyed to give my sweet Betty <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>, which I did. . . . <ref target="#clinton.010.intro36">36</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro36" n="36">Ibid., 91-92.</note>  Thornton also nurses a later child, Robert, "all along while I was with <orig reg="child">childe</orig> and till about a fortnight before my delivery" of her eighth child, Joyce, in 1665. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro37">37</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro37" n="37">Ibid., 144-145.</note>  Custom and medical advice aside, she seems highly motivated to nurse her children.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13069">Thornton comments about nursing her sixth child, William, born in April of 1660, are particularly illustrative:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13071"><q>[M]y pretty babe was in good health, <orig reg="sucking">suckeing</orig> his poor mother, to whom my good God had given the blessing of the breast as well as the womb, of that <orig reg="child">childe</orig> to 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13070" n="xiv"/>
whom it was no little satisfaction, while I <orig reg="enjoyed">injoyed</orig> his life; and the joy of it made me <orig reg="recruit">recrute</orig> faster, for his sake, that I might do my duty to him as a mother.  But it pleased God to shorten this joy, least I be too much transported. . . .</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro38">38</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro38" n="38">Ibid., 124.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13072">Thornton again displays her unequivocal commitment to breastfeeding in this passage.  She suggests that nursing gave both her and her son great joy, so much that God felt it necessary to curtail that joy by taking the boy's life after only a few days.  But nursing is also connected to her sense of maternal obligation--she wants to "do [her] duty to him as a mother," just as the moral advice tracts recommend.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13073">Belying Thornton's rank, her <title>Autobiography</title> records that she also nursed all her subsequent children, one until the age of two.  Her entries about childbirth consistently mention nursing, suggesting she felt it noteworthy many years after her children were grown.  This focus on nursing also seems to be at odds with Thornton's professed Anglican and Royalist beliefs; although she may have been influenced by the Puritan climate of the 1650s, none of her commentaries about political events demonstrates any sympathy for Parliamentary forces or for nonconformist religious practice.  Yet she nursed (and recorded her feelings about nursing) just as Puritan texts recommended.  So, despite her social milieu and the pervasive disapproval of women of rank lowering themselves to breastfeeding, Thornton nursed her children whenever she was physically able because it made her feel like a dutiful mother.  Although she suffered from a variety of serious illnesses, ranging from gangrene of the breast to jaundice, she never employed a wet nurse for her children unless illness physically prevented her from nursing.  This devotion to breastfeeding seems to imply that, as the moralists recommend, Thornton equated breastfeeding with good motherhood.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13075">Few women were as deeply committed to maternal breastfeeding as Alice Thornton.  Despite the numerous moralistic tracts of the seventeenth century--of which <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> discussed below is a primary example--Thornton's and other women's experiences demonstrate that families responded individually to the discordant messages about 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13074" n="xv"/>
breastfeeding.  The ambivalence of medical texts, combined with the intense rhetorical efforts to promote maternal breastfeeding in moral advice tracts, created a battle between custom and conscience.  As part of the concerted effort to define and regulate maternal behavior during the seventeenth century, the conflict over breastfeeding is a powerful example of how hard the battle was fought, and how far short of victory the moralists often fell.</p></div><div xml:id="clinton_007" n="5" type="Section"><head>V.<lb/><seg type="short-title">Joining in the Discourse</seg>:<lb/><title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title></head><p xml:id="clinton_13076">Like Alice Thornton, who so intimately connects breastfeeding with good motherhood, Elizabeth Clinton's <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> directly links maternal nursing with being a good mother.  Furthermore, as part of the frequently antagonistic seventeenth-century debate over breastfeeding, Clinton's tract is a more important contribution than has hitherto been acknowledged.  Clinton's published views indicate both her Puritan tendencies <ref target="#clinton.010.intro39">39</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro39" n="39">See the Biographical Essay, xxiii.</note> and her participation in the lively cultural debate carried on throughout the century.  The power and variety of her prose reveals not only her belief in the duty, benefit, and joy of maternal nursing, but also the rhetorical skill and energy she devoted to the cause.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13078">Much of <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> explicitly concerns the spiritual--not just medical or social--duty of a woman to breastfeed her children.  But because she is a mother, she mourns her personal failure to breastfeed.  Remorse for employing a wet nurse for all eighteen of her own children, for (as she says later) bidding another woman to "unlove her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> to love [mine]" <ref target="#clinton.010.intro40">40</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro40" n="40">Elizabeth Clinton, <title>The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> (London, 1622), D2r.</note> remains a small but important factor in <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>.  Part of what drives the tract, along with the author's desire for spiritual reform, is Elizabeth Clinton's 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13077" n="xvi"/>
yearning for expiation of her personal failure to nurse.  As a sincere Christian, Clinton wants to exculpate herself, and by doing so, prevent other women from committing the same sin.  She admits, "I <orig reg="know">knowe</orig> and acknowledge that I should have done it, and having not done it, it was not for want of will in my self, but <hi rend="italic">partly I was overruled by <orig reg="another's">anothers</orig> authority,. . .  partly I had not so well considered of my duty in this motherly office</hi>, as since I did, when it was too late for me to put it into execution." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro41">41</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro41" n="41">Ibid., C4r-D1v.</note>  A victim of custom and youth, Clinton allowed her maternal instincts to be "overruled."   She further admits to being "pricked in hart for my undutifulness, this way I study to <orig reg="redeem">redeeme</orig> my peace."<ref target="#clinton.010.intro42">42</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro42" n="42">Ibid., D1v.</note>  Thus, promoting maternal breastfeeding in her old age helps Clinton enact a sort of restitution for sins of her youth.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13079">But her focus on a personal transgression is far from being Clinton's only rhetorical tool.  Although she uses her own failure to nurse as a persuasive tactic, Clinton also musters her social status to attack other women who shun breastfeeding for frivolous social reasons.  For what she calls the "vain lusts" of convenience, extra sleep, beauty, and prestige, she attacks her peers who abandon their duty to breastfeed.  She scornfully addresses the common objections to maternal nursing:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13080"><q>Secondly it is objected, that it is troublesome; that it is <orig reg="noisome">noysome</orig> to ones clothes; that it makes one <orig reg="look">looke</orig> old, &amp;c. All such reasons are uncomely, and unchristian to be objected: and therefore unworthy to be answered, they argue <hi rend="italic">unmotherly affection, <orig reg="idleness">idlenesse</orig>, desire to have liberty to gadd from home, pride, <orig reg="foolishness">foolishnesse</orig>, lust, <orig reg="wantonness">wantonnesse</orig></hi>, &amp; the like <orig reg="evils">evills</orig>. . . .  behold most nursing mothers, and they be as <orig reg="clean">cleane</orig> and sweet in their <orig reg="clothes">cloathes</orig>, and carry their age, and hold their <orig reg="beauty">beautie</orig>, as well as those that suckle not and most likely are they so to <orig reg="do">doe</orig>, because keeping God's <hi rend="italic">Ordinance</hi>, they are sure of Gods <hi rend="italic">Blessing</hi>: and it hath <orig reg="been">beene</orig> observed in some women that they grew more <orig reg="beautiful">beautifull</orig>, and better favoured, by very nursing their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro43">43</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro43" n="43">Ibid., C2v.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13082">Although Clinton employ religious arguments here, she focuses on women's vanity; but, she links this same vanity to a series of moral failures, including "pride, lust, and wantonness," 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13081" n="xvii"/>
paralleling failure to nurse with two of the seven deadly sins.  Finally, she also asserts that the idleness of these wealthy, vain, non-nursing mothers leads to their greater independence, "a desire to have liberty to gadd from home."  Clinton wants to show that hiring a nurse leads down a path that no Christian woman ought to tread.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13083"><title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title> eventually becomes personal in its assault on wealthy women, perhaps because the author was literally speaking to her peers.  Clinton proclaims:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13084"><q>And this unthankfullness and unnaturalness is <orig reg="oftener">oftner</orig> the <orig reg="sin">sinne</orig> of the <hi rend="italic">Higher</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">richer</hi> sort then of the meaner, and poorer, except some nice, and proud idle dames, who will imitate their betters. . . . And this is one hurt which the better <orig reg="rank">ranke</orig><orig reg="do">doe</orig> by their ill example; egge and <orig reg="embolden">imbolden</orig> the lower ones to follow them to their <orig reg="loss">losse</orig>: were it not better for Us greater persons to <orig reg="keep">keepe</orig> God's ordinance &amp; to shew the meaner their <orig reg="duty">dutie</orig> in our good example?  I am sure wee have more <orig reg="helps">helpes</orig> to <orig reg="perform">performe</orig> it, and have fewer probable reasons to <orig reg="allege">alleage</orig> against it then women that live by hard labour and <orig reg="painful">painfull</orig> toile.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro44">44</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro44" n="44">Ibid., C2r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13085">Clinton sees the consistent use of wet nurses by the nobility and gentry as a social evil, with the ill-advised customs of the wealthy corrupting the lower ranks.  Speaking to her peers, "Us greater persons," she tries to convince these women that maternal nursing is an important demonstration of social, as well as religious, responsibility.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13087">Clinton does, however, seem to show some sympathy to women whose duties include both their daily work in the fields or home and the nursing of children. Her concern with the economic discrepancies involved in breastfeeding becomes evident when she pleads with wealthy women, "Therefore no longer be at the trouble, and at the care to hire others to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> your <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="work">worke</orig></hi> .. . . bee not <hi rend="italic">accessary</hi> to that disorder of causing a <hi rend="italic">poorer woman to banish her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> infant</hi> for the entertaining of a <hi rend="italic">richer <orig reg="woman's">womans</orig> child</hi>, as it were, bidding her <hi rend="italic">unlove her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> to love yours</hi>." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro45">45</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro45" n="45">Ibid., D2v-D2r.</note>  Clinton's perspective on wet nursing is clearly skewed by her social position, but her status does not prevent her from seeing the problems it creates on all economic levels.
<pb xml:id="clinton_13086" n="xviii"/></p><p xml:id="clinton_13088">Although Clinton employs a variety of social and economic approaches for rhetorical purposes, much of her treatise promotes spiritual reform: she wants to recall mothers to their Christian duty.  In the dedicatory letter to her daughter-in-law Briget Clinton, she calls breastfeeding "a duty, which all mothers are bound to <orig reg="perform">performe</orig>" in order to be to be answerable to "all holy commands of the Holy God." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro46">46</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro46" n="46">Ibid.,  A3r.</note>  Clinton also ties maternal breastfeeding to the essence of being a good Christian woman and the performance of the duty as a daily lesson in right living: "<orig reg="Think">Thinke</orig> again how your Babe crying at your breast, sucking heartily the <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> out of it and growing by it, is the <hi rend="italic">Lords <orig reg="own">owne</orig> instruction</hi>, every <orig reg="hour">houre</orig>, and every day that you are suckling it, instructing you to shew that you are his <hi rend="italic">new borne Babes</hi>, by your earnest desire after his word. . . . <ref target="#clinton.010.intro47">47</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro47" n="47">Ibid., D3v.</note>  The figurative nursing performed by God to all Christians, which is referred to in Peter 2:2, <ref target="#clinton.010.intro48">48</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro48" n="48">1 Peter 2:2-3 states "As <orig reg="newborn">newborne</orig> babes desire the <orig reg="sincere">syncere</orig> milk of the word, that ye may <orig reg="grow">growe</orig> thereby.  It so be that ye have tasted how <orig reg="bountiful">bountifull</orig> is the Lord."  See <title>The Geneva Bible: A Facsimile of the 1560 Edition</title>, Introduction by Lloyd Berry (Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1969).  It seems likely from an examination of other Biblical allusions in Clinton's work that she used the Geneva Bible so popular among  nonconformists, rather than the Authorized Version.</note> is strengthened by the literal nursing relationship between a mother and child.  Clinton wants women to do their duty to God, to their children, and to their own souls by breastfeeding whenever they are able.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13089">Clinton also couches the choice not to breastfeed as willful disobedience to God's words, castigating those women who chose "their own pleasures" above the "<orig reg="express">expresse</orig><hi rend="italic">ordinance</hi> of God that mothers should nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro49">49</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro49" n="49"><title>The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, B2v.</note>  Clinton, however, carefully delineates who is excused from the duty:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13091"><q>O <orig reg="do">doe</orig><orig reg="know">knowe</orig> that the Lord may deny some women, either to have any <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> in their breasts at all, or to have passage for their <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, or to have any health, or to have a right <orig reg="mind">minde</orig>: and so they may be letted from this duty, by <hi rend="italic">want</hi>, by <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="sickness">sicknesse</orig></hi>, by <hi rend="italic">lunacy</hi>, &amp;c.  But I <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> not to these: I <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> to you whose 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13090" n="xix"/>
consciences <orig reg="witness">witnes</orig> against you, that you cannot justly <orig reg="allege">alleage</orig> any of those impediments.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro50">50</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro50" n="50">Ibid., D1r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13092">Clinton addresses women directly, clearly indicating her audience and her mission as a preacher.  Her direct address to women, "you whose consciences <orig reg="witness">witnes</orig> against you," marks her text as a lecture, even a sermon.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13093">Clinton's language becomes more intense as her argument about the spiritual necessity of breastfeeding progresses.  She actively worries about the state of women's souls, crying out "Oh what peace can there be to these <orig reg="women's">womens</orig> consciences, unless through the <orig reg="darkness">darknesse</orig> of their understanding they judge it no disobedience." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro51">51</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro51" n="50">Ibid., B2v.</note>  At the height of her lecture, Clinton exclaims:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13094"><q>Oh consider, how comes our <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>?  Is it not by the direct providence of God?  Why provides he it, but for the child? The mothers then that refuse to nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children, <orig reg="do">doe</orig> they not despise Gods providence?  Doe they not deny Gods will. . . . Oh impious, and impudent unthankfullness; yea, monstrous unnaturalness, both to their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> natural fruit borne so <orig reg="near">neare</orig> their breasts, and fed in their <orig reg="wombs">wombes</orig>, and yet may not be suffered to <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> their <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="milk">milke</orig>.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro52">52</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro52" n="52">Ibid., C2v-C2r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_13095">Moving away from the sympathy of earlier passages, Clinton's tone becomes noticeably strident.  She is, in essence, preaching.  Instead of framing her argument in terms of women's modesty and duty, she turns the use of wet nurses into a bona fide sin.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13097">It is clear from even a brief examination of other Puritan texts about breastfeeding that Elizabeth Clinton, by writing and publishing <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, contributes to the lively early modern cultural and religious debates about appropriate maternal behavior.  Twentieth-century historians have not been so willing to allow Clinton a role in these discursive efforts to regulate maternity.  Antonia Fraser, for instance, believes that Clinton wrote her tract merely because she, like so many other women, had encountered neglectful nurses and wanted to prevent any further loss of life; she elides Clinton's intense religious motivation, and the preaching it inspired.  Other feminist studies relegate Clinton's work into the limiting category of 
<pb xml:id="clinton_13096" n="xx"/>
a woman writing to other women "for the benefit of their own sex." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro53">53</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro53" n="53">Patricia Crawford, "The Construction and Experience of Maternity in Seventeenth Century England," in <title>Women as Mothers in Pre-Industrial England</title>, ed. Valerie Fildes (London: Routledge: 1990), 3-38.  See also Suzanne Hull, <title>Chaste, Silent, and Obedient: English Books for Women, 1475-1640</title> (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1982).  Large portions of Clinton's tract have been recently reproduced and lightly edited in two volumes of primary documents about early modern women.  See Kate Aughterson's <title>Renaissance Woman: A Sourcebook, Constructions of Femininity in England</title> (London: Routledge, 1995.  116-120); and <title>Lay By Your Needles Ladies, Take the Pen: Writing Women n England, 1500-1700</title>, ed. Suzanne Trill, Kate Chedgzoy, and Melanie Osborne (London: Arnold Press, 1997.  119-124).</note>  However, analysis of how influential Clinton's preaching and this same-gender interaction might have been is lacking in all modern critical works about <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>.</p><p xml:id="clinton_13098">Margaret King, for instance, places severe limitations on Clinton's work:</p><p xml:id="clinton_13099"><q>Such works [women authored texts] were private and personal, and did not claim to enter upon the masculine territory of literary production.  They drew on personal experience and were addressed to an intimate circle.  As the English Countess of Lincoln Elizabeth Knevet Clinton explained, amid pages of exhortation to her daughter in law about the proper care and nurture of her children, "I leave the larger and learneder discourse here-of unto men of art, and learning: only I speak of so much as I <orig reg="read">reade</orig> and know in mine <orig reg="own">owne</orig> experience, which if any of my <orig reg="sex">sexe</orig> and condition do <orig reg="receive">receave</orig> good by, I am glad."</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro54">54</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro54" n="54">Margaret L. King, <title>Women of the Renaissance</title> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1991), 214.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130100">By concluding that Clinton herself restricted her work, King neglects an important literary trope.  Although Clinton's meek "I leave the larger and learneder discourse here-of unto men of art" seems to efface her authority as a writer, it is, in fact, a standard ploy of the woman writer (and of many male writers, too) in the early modern period.  As Margaret Ezell observes, "Read in this company [of amateur male writers], women authors seem no more modest than their male contemporaries; rather than pleading pressing business or spiritual concerns which prevent the author from attempting true scholarship as many male writers do, they simply plead their sex." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro55">55</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro55" n="55">Margaret J.M. Ezell, <title>The Patriarch's Wife: Literary Evidence and the History of the Family</title> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1987), 88.</note>  In this context, Clinton finesses a literary tactic to make her writing more effective.  By partially obscuring her own authority, Clinton seems less strident and thus more feminine, which in turn authenticates her voice and her opinions.</p><pb xml:id="clinton_130101" n="xxi"/><p xml:id="clinton_130102">By rhetorically manipulating her femininity, Clinton knows she confers authority on her tract:</p><p xml:id="clinton_130103"><q>Because it hath pleased God to <orig reg="bless">blesse</orig> me with so many children, and so caused me to observe many things falling out to mothers, and to their children; I thought it good to open my <orig reg="mind">minde</orig> concerning a <orig reg="special">speciall</orig> matter belonging to all <orig reg="child">childe</orig>-bearing women, seriously to consider of: and to manifest my <orig reg="mind">minde</orig> the better, even to write of this matter, so <orig reg="far">farre</orig> as God shall please to direct me.</q><ref target="#clinton.010.intro56">56</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro56" n="56">Clinton, <title>The Countess of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, B1r.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130104">At this point, she specifically situates herself as a mother speaking to other mothers--her maternal experience provides justification for publishing her views, and she does so only "so <orig reg="far">farre</orig> as God shall please to direct" her.  By the end of the tract, though, she states that her purpose in writing is "by doing my endeavor to prevent many Christian mothers from sinning in the same kind, against our most loving and <orig reg="gracious">gratious</orig> God." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro57">57</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro57" n="57">Ibid., D1v.</note>  Her impetus to prevent sin by publicly lecturing women is only marginally tempered by her claim that "I write in <orig reg="modesty">modestie</orig>." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro58">58</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro58" n="58">Ibid., C3v.</note>  Although she is "direct[ed]" by God, Clinton asserts herself and her moral beliefs to teach her peers.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130105">In this light, then, Elizabeth Clinton, the Countess of Lincoln, is not merely a woman writing to other women, or a concerned mother hoping to save her daughters and grandchildren from sin and danger.  In part, she is a Christian voice speaking out to other Christians, exhorting and preaching to them about their duties to God; in part, she is a noblewoman using her place and her authority to appeal to her peers; and in part, she is a writer working to stabilize the vexed position of parents affected by the cultural ambivalence about maternal breastfeeding.  The annotated text that follows clearly demonstrates that through effective and varied rhetoric, Clinton inserts herself, her voice and opinions, into a discourse on proper and godly childbearing.</p><pb xml:id="clinton_130106" n="xxii"/></div><div xml:id="clinton_008" n="6" type="Preface"><head>VI.<lb/>
Editorial Practice</head><p xml:id="clinton_130107">I have designed the edition which follows with both the scholar and student of early modern literature in mind.  I have left the original punctuation and spelling as they appear in the 1622 first edition.  I have, for the sake of clarity, silently emended i/j, f/s, u/v, and vv/w.  I have also retained the original orthography and italicization since they covey emphasis unavailable in purely Roman typeface.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130108">When annotating the text, I provided extensive Biblical citation and quotation to allow the reader to more fully grasp the rich tapestry Clinton weaves using Scripture as her guide; from personal experience I also know that a reference to a Bible chapter and verse is not as instructive--due to basic laziness--as the full text of one is.  I likewise gloss  unusual vocabulary, as well as references to further reading, when I believe it would be helpful.</p></div><pb xml:id="clinton_130109" n="xxiii"/><div xml:id="clinton_009" n="7" type="Biography"><head>VII.<lb/>
Biographical Essay</head><p xml:id="clinton_130110">Elizabeth Knevet, daughter of Sir Henry Knevet and Anne Pickering, was born in Charlton, Wiltshire, in 1574, the year her father was knighted by Queen Elizabeth I.  Although her birth is not recorded in the parish register for Charlton, it is recorded in the family Bible. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro59">59</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro59" n="59"><title>The Feminist Companion to Literature in English</title> (eds. Virginia Blain et.al., New Haven: Yale University Press, 1991) lists her mother as Elizabeth Stumpe.  <title>The Encyclopedia of British Women Writers</title> (eds. Pal Schulter and Jane Schulter.  New York: Garland, 1988) gives the name Anne Pickering, as well as including the information about dating Clinton's birth.</note> The Knevets were a genteel family of some fortune,  although generally unimportant in court; Elizabeth's brother Thomas did rise to power in the reign of King James I, when he became a Gentleman of the Bedchamber to James, as well as receiving a baronetcy on July 4, 1607 for his role as Justice of the Peace for Westminster in helping to unmask the Gunpowder Plot in 1605. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro60">60</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro60" n="60">Sir Bernard Burke, <title>Burke's Dormant and Extinct Peerages</title> (London: Harrison Booksellers, 1883), 472.</note> Her sister, Susanna, was married to the powerful nobleman, Thomas Howard, earl of Suffolk.  Clearly, the Knevets commanded sufficient status and wealth to ensure that their male children obtained rank and privilege through politics, and that marriage did the same for the female offspring.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130112">Elizabeth Knevet's date of birth is corroborated by a statement in the <title>Knyvett Letters</title> that at the age of ten, Elizabeth Knevet was married to Thomas Clinton in 1584. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro61">61</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro61" n="61"><title>The Biographical Dictionary of British Women Writers, 1580-1720</title> (ed. Maureen Bell.  Boston: G.K. Hall, 1990)  lists the Knyvett Letters (Norfolk Records Society, 1949) as the source of information about Clinton's marriage.</note> Her husband, Thomas Clinton, was born in 1571, and was the Eleventh Baron Clinton and Third Earl of Lincoln; he inherited these titles at the death of his father in 1610, before which he and his wife were simply Lord and Lady Clinton.  The Clintons are, according to <title>Burke's Dormant and</title><pb xml:id="clinton_130111" n="xxiv"/><title>Extinct Peerages</title>, the ancestors of the extant Dukes of Newcastle. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro62">62</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro62" n="62"><title>Burke's Dormant and Extinct Peerages</title>, 472.</note>  As Lady Clinton and Countess of Lincoln, Elizabeth Clinton bore her husband, according to her own account, eighteen children.  She states near the end of her essay that "of all those [nurses] which I had for my <orig reg="eighteen">eighteene</orig> children, I had but two which were throughly willing and <orig reg="careful">carefull</orig>."  <title>The Female Spectator</title> notes that the children were seven sons and nine daughters, "few of whom survived childhood." <ref target="#clinton.010.intro63">63</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro63" n="63">Mary R. Mahl and Helene Koon, <title>The Female Spectator: Women Writers Before 1800</title> (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1977) 88.</note> Thomas Clinton died in 1618, and at the probating of his will in 1620, the couple had seven surviving children: one son, Theophilus, who inherited his father's title and lands, and six daughters, Fraunces, Arabella, Susan, Dorcas, Sara, and Elizabeth.  One of them, Arabella, emigrated to New England with the John Winthrop party in 1629, but died shortly after arriving at the Massachusetts Bay Colony. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro64">64</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro64" n="64">Ibid., 89.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130113">Elizabeth Clinton was thus Dowager Countess of Lincoln when she composed and published <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, which she dedicated to her daughter-in-law, Briget Clinton.  Through Briget, Clinton had nine grandchildren, and it is their mother's virtuous behavior that inspires the treatise.  Although Clinton styles the tract "the first <orig reg="work">worke</orig> of mine that ever came in Print," none else survive.  Clinton herself died in 1630, eight years after the publication of <title>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</title>, and is buried in the parish church in Great Grimsby, Lincolnshire. <ref target="#clinton.010.intro65">65</ref><note xml:id="clinton.010.intro65" n="65"><title>Encyclopedia of British Women Writers</title>, 109.</note></p><pb xml:id="clinton_130114" n="xxv"/></div></div></div><div xml:id="clinton_011" type="Book"><head>The Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie</head><docAuthor>Clinton, Elizabeth Knevet</docAuthor><p xml:id="clinton_130115">THE<lb/>
COUNTESSE<lb/>
OF LINCOLNES<lb/>
NURSERIE</p><p xml:id="clinton_130116">AT OXFORD</p><p xml:id="clinton_130118">Printed by John Lichfield and James Short, Printers to 
the famous Universitie, 1622.<pb xml:id="clinton_130117" n="2"/></p><div xml:id="clinton_012" type="Dedication"><head><seg type="short-title">To the Right Honorable</seg>, and approved <orig reg="virtuous">vertuous</orig> Lady, <lb/>
Briget, Countesse of Lincolne</head><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse1">1</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse1" n="1">Briget Clinton, Countess of Lincoln, was the author's daughter-in-law, that is, the wife of Elizabeth Clinton's son Theophilus, who succeeded as fourth Earl of Lincoln at his father's death in 1619.  Accordingly to William Oldys, the editor of <title>The Harleian Miscellany</title> (Vol. IV.  London: White and Co., 1809), Briget Clinton had two sons and seven daughters.</note><p xml:id="clinton_130120">For the better expressing &amp; keeping in <orig reg="memory">memorie</orig> of my Love, and your Worthines, I do offer unto your Ladyship: the first <orig reg="work">worke</orig> of mine that ever came into Print <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse2">2</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse2" n="2">This statement would seem to imply that Elizabeth Clinton has other literary works; none are known extant.  See the entry on Clinton in Paul Schuleter and June Schuleter, eds.  <title>An Encyclopedia of British Women Writers</title> (New York: Garland, 1988) 109.</note>; because your rare example, hath given me an excellent approbation to the matter contained in this <orig reg="Book">Booke</orig>; for you have passed by all excuses, and have ventured upon, &amp; <orig reg="do">doe</orig><orig reg="go">goe</orig> on with that loving act of a loving mother; in giving the <orig reg="sweet">sweete</orig><orig reg="milk">milke</orig> of your <orig reg="own">owne</orig> breasts <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse3">3</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse3" n="3">Although this line has a Biblical savor, no applicable Biblical quotations have been located.  The focus on the sweetness of the milk is consistent, however, with medical literature of the time.  See <title>The Complete Midwife's Practice</title> (1663), as well as Jane Sharp's <title>The Midwives Book</title> (1671) which notes that breast milk "must be white and sweet scented, if it smell <orig reg="sour">sowr</orig> or burnt, it will corrupt the stomach" (<title>Brown Women Writers Project Draft in Process</title>, 151.)  The statement is thus both literal and figurative.</note>, to your <orig reg="own">owne</orig> child; wherein you have gone before the greatest number of honourable Ladies of your place, in these latter times. But I wish many may follow you, in this good work, which I desire, to further by my kind persuasion.  And such women as will vouchsafe to read this little treatise; may be put in mind of a duty, which all mothers are bound to <orig reg="perform">performe</orig>; and I shall be glad if any will consider, and put in practice, that which is both <orig reg="natural">naturall</orig> and comfortable.  I hope they will at the least commend with me such as do this good <orig reg="deed">deede</orig>, and no more <orig reg="speak">speake</orig><orig reg="scornfully">scornefully</orig> of that which is worthy of great praise; and for my part I <orig reg="think">thinke</orig> it an honour unto you, to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> that which hath proved you to be 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130119" n="3"/>
full of care to please God, and of <orig reg="natural">naturall</orig> affection, and to bee well stored with humility, and patience, all of which are highly to be praised; to give praise to any person or thing deserving praise, I dare <orig reg="do">doe</orig> it, &amp; and for this lovely action of yours I can with much <orig reg="thankfulness">thankfulnesse</orig> praise God, for all his gracious gifts of grace and Nature, whereby he hath <orig reg="enabled">inabled</orig> you, to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> the same: desiring also with my heart, that you may ever, and every way honour God, who hath honoured you many <orig reg="ways">wayes</orig>, above many women; and I rejoice, that I can <orig reg="bear">beare</orig><orig reg="witness">witnes</orig>, that God hath adorned you with faire tokens of his love <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse4">4</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse4" n="4">I.e., children.</note> and mercy to your <orig reg="soul">soule</orig>; As the practice of true Christian religion; dedicating your <orig reg="self">selfe</orig> to Gods service; answerablenesse to all holy commands of the holy God, which are Testimonies of Gods love, and doth challenge a very great <orig reg="esteem">esteeme</orig> from me, amongst the rest, that can truly judge and rightly <orig reg="discern">discerne</orig> what is best <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse5">5</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse5" n="5">Clinton seems to be paraphrasing Luke 12:57 here: "And why judge ye not of your fellows what is right?"  In general, Clinton seems to quote or paraphrase the 1561 Geneva Bible, rather than the Authorized Version of 1611.</note>; I am full of thoughts in this kind or of this matter: yet I say no more but this, <orig reg="Go">Goe</orig> on and prosper, Hold fast all that is good, trust in God for strength to grow <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse6">6</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse6" n="6">A general tenet, but also an oblique reference to 1 Peter 2:2-3, "As <orig reg="newborn">newborne</orig> babes desire the <orig reg="sincere">syncyre</orig><orig reg="milk">milke</orig> of the word, that ye may <orig reg="grow">growe</orig> thereby. It so be that ye have tasted how <orig reg="bountiful">bountifull</orig> is the Lord."</note> and continue in <orig reg="faithful">faithfull</orig> obedience to his glorious majesty, And I will not cease to <orig reg="entreat">intreat</orig> the Lord of heaven, to <orig reg="power">powre</orig><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse7">7</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse7" n="7">I.e., pour.</note><orig reg="abundantly">aboundantly</orig> all Blessings of heaven and earth upon you, and your children, as they increase in number.Your Ladyship: in the best and fastest <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse8">8</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse8" n="8">In this sense, "fastest" means earnest and steady (OED). <title>The Harleian Miscellany</title> reprints it as "safest," but in the UMI microfilm of the 1622 edition, it is clearly an "f."</note> love ELIZABETH LINCOLNE.</p><pb xml:id="clinton_130121" n="4"/></div><div xml:id="clinton_013" type="Preface"><head><seg type="short-title">Preface</seg> to the Countesse of Lincolnes Nurserie: TO THE COURTEOUS, chiefly most Christian, Reader</head><p xml:id="clinton_130122">TO THE COURTEOUS,<lb/>
chiefly most Christian, Reader.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130124"><hi rend="italic">The <orig reg="General">Generall</orig> Consent of too many mothers in an <orig reg="unnatural">unnaturall</orig> practise, (most Christian Reader) hath caused one of the Noblest and Fairest hands in this land to set pen to paper.  As ashamed to see her sex farther degenerate;</hi> desirous <hi rend="italic">for the glory thereof, to have all both rightly know, and <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> their kind,</hi><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse9">9</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse9" n="9">"Kind" here means more than just "type."  It carries the additional meanings of "nature," "birth (i.e. nobility)," and "gender" (OED).</note> hath made Honour <hi rend="italic">it <orig reg="self">selfe</orig> stoop to these <orig reg="pains">paines</orig>; which now <orig reg="she">shee</orig> sends thee to peruse</hi>. Three things <hi rend="italic">easily invite to read what to view is <orig reg="offered">offred</orig></hi>.  Eminency, or Interest <hi rend="italic">in the Author</hi>, rarity <hi rend="italic">in the handled Matter;</hi> Brevity <hi rend="italic">in the <orig reg="quick">quicke</orig> dispatch. These three meet in this won.</hi><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse10">10</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse10" n="10">Apparently a printer's error or alternative spelling.  I believe the sense supports "one."</note>  The Author so eminent in Honor; <hi rend="italic">thou canst hardly be anciently</hi> Honourable; <hi rend="italic">and not be interested in her</hi> Honours acquaintance; <hi rend="italic">scarcely not</hi> Alliance.  <hi rend="italic">Next for the</hi> Rareness, <hi rend="italic">a peculiar tract of this subject, I believe, is not in thine hands</hi>. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse11">11</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse11" n="11">Lodge is correct here.  Only one other exclusive treatment of this topic has been located, Henry Newcome's 1695 treatise, <title>The Compleat Mother, or an Earnest Perswasive to Mothers. . .</title> Other discussions of the necessity and godliness of maternal breastfeeding are all embedded in longer moral tracts and medical works, such as William Gouge's popular <title>Of Domestical Duties</title> (London, 1622).  See the Introduction, Section II for further discussion.</note> Lastly, it is so <orig reg="brief">briefe</orig>, <hi rend="italic">as I am <orig reg="persuaded">perswaded</orig>, it smoothly gliding thee along in the reading, Thy sorrow will be, it lands</hi><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse12">12</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse12" n="12">"Lands" in the sense of brings to shore, thus ending a journey.</note> thee so <orig reg="soon">soone</orig>.  <hi rend="italic">What may give satisfaction of a Reader, let me acquaint thee next, is here to be</hi> found.  <hi rend="italic">These are</hi> two things; Usefulness <hi rend="italic">of the subject;</hi> Fulness <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse13">13</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse13" n="13">"Fulness" here means "completeness" or "perfection" (OED).  See, for instance the phrase from the <title>Book of Common Prayer</title>, "the fulness of thy grace."</note><hi rend="italic">for the prosecution. If</hi> method and <orig reg="soundness">soundnesse</orig><hi rend="italic">can make Full, this is Full. What not alone</hi> Confirmation <hi rend="italic">ushering in the</hi> Assertion, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> Refutation,  
<pb xml:id="clinton_130123" n="5"/><hi rend="italic">for ushering out</hi> Objections <hi rend="italic">can <orig reg="do">doe</orig> to making</hi> Sound and Through, <hi rend="italic">this is</hi> Such. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse14">14</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse14" n="14">A difficult phrase due to its Latinate syntax.  I believe Lodge is saying "This work is sound and thorough since not only are the author's assertions confirmed, but also any objections are carefully ushered out."</note><hi rend="italic">The</hi> Accommodation <hi rend="italic">to these particulars (Gentle Reader) I Leave to thy <orig reg="self">selfe</orig>, least because I am</hi> tedious <hi rend="italic">while I am honoring</hi> Brevity.  <hi rend="italic">The Pay assure thy <orig reg="self">selfe</orig>, will bee larger then the</hi> promise. <hi rend="italic">The</hi> Wine <hi rend="italic">much better than the</hi> Bush. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse15">15</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse15" n="15">An apparently proverbial statement, but its source is unknown.</note><hi rend="italic">This one word, and Ile stand out of the gate, thou mayst <orig reg="go">goe</orig> in. If</hi> Noble <hi rend="italic">who readest,</hi> (<orig reg="likeness">likenesse</orig> is Mother and Nurse of liking <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse16">16</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse16" n="16">A proverbial expression.  <title>The Dictionary of Sixteenth and Seventeenth Century Proverbs</title>, ed. Morris Tilley Palmer, ( Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1950) cites Clinton as an example of this phrase.</note>) <hi rend="italic">this comes from Nobility;</hi> Approve <hi rend="italic">the rather, and</hi> practise. <hi rend="italic">If</hi> meaner; <hi rend="italic">blush to deny what</hi> Honour <hi rend="italic">becomes speaker to <orig reg="persuade">purswade</orig> to,</hi> president <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse17">17</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse17" n="17">"President" used as an adjective, i.e. "one who presides over or superintends" (OED).</note><hi rend="italic">to lead the way to.  And so I either</hi> humbly <hi rend="italic">take my leave; or bid farewell.</hi></p><lg type="stanza"><l>Blest is the land where sons of Nobles <orig reg="reign">raigne</orig>.</l><l>Blest is the land where Nobles teach their <orig reg="train">traine</orig>. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse18">18</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse18" n="18">"Traine" meaning "band of followers to a noble" (OED).</note></l><l>To church for <orig reg="bliss">blisse</orig> great Kings, <orig reg="Queens">Queenes</orig>, should Nurses be. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse19">19</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse19" n="19">Lodge paraphrases Isaiah 49:23, "Kings shall be thy nursing fathers, and Queens shall be thy <orig reg="nurses">nourses</orig>."</note></l><l>To state its <orig reg="bliss">blisse</orig> great Dames Babes nurse to see.</l><l>Go then, Great <orig reg="book">booke</orig> of Nursing plead the Cause.</l><l>Teach High'st, lov'st all, it's Gods and Natures <orig reg="laws">lawes</orig>.</l></lg><p xml:id="clinton_130125">Thomas Lodge <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse20">20</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse20" n="20">The Brown Women Writers Draft in Process of the <title>Nurserie</title> lists the initials only here.  The UMI microfilm gives the author's full name, Thomas Lodge.  Lodge (1558-1625) was a recusant Catholic solicitor, author, privateer, and physician.  He is most famous for his 1590 romance, <title>Rosalynde</title>, one of Shakespeare's sources for <title>As You Like It</title>.</note></p><pb xml:id="clinton_130126" n="6"/></div><div xml:id="clinton_014" type="Text"><head>THE COUNTESSE OF<lb/>
Lincolnes Nurserie</head><p xml:id="clinton_130127">Because it hath pleased God to <orig reg="bless">blesse</orig> me with many children, and so caused me to observe many things falling out to mothers, and to their children; I thought good to open my <orig reg="mind">minde</orig> concerning a <orig reg="special">speciall</orig> matter belonging to all <orig reg="child">childe</orig>-bearing women, seriously to consider of: and to manifest my <orig reg="mind">minde</orig> the better even to write of this matter, so <orig reg="far">farr</orig> as God shall please to direct me <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse21">21</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse21" n="21">This is the traditional pose of the Renaissance woman writer-she must use God's direction as an impetus to write.  See Charlotte Otten's <title>English Women's Voices, 1540-1720</title> (Miami: Florida International Press, 1992) for multiple examples, especially in the sections on mother's advice books and the female prophets of the seventeenth century.</note>; in <orig reg="sum">sume</orig>, the matter I mean, <hi rend="italic">Is the duty of nursing due by mothers to their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children.</hi></p><p xml:id="clinton_130128">In setting <orig reg="down">downe</orig> whereof, I <orig reg="will">wil</orig> first shew that every woman ought to nurse her <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="child">childe</orig>; and secondly, I will endeavour to <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> such objections, as are used to be cast out against this <orig reg="duty">dutie</orig> to disgrace the same.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130130">The first point is easily performed. For it is the <orig reg="express">expresse</orig><hi rend="italic">ordinance</hi> of God that mothers nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse22">22</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse22" n="22">Clinton derives this injunction from many scattered Biblical passages, one of most obvious being Isaiah 49:15, "Can a woman forget her child, and not have compassion for the son her womb?" She does, however, neglect to use the following verse ("Though they <orig reg="should">shuld</orig> forget, yet I [God] will not forget thee") which implies that the maternal bond is breakable.  The Authorized Version inserts the word "sucking" before "child," so it is possible Clinton was thinking of it as well.</note> &amp; being his ordinance they are bound to it in conscience.  This 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130129" n="7"/>
should stop the <orig reg="mouths">mouthes</orig> of all replyers, for God is most wise <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse23">23</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse23" n="23">[Author's note: Isaiah 31:2] The Scripture reads "But he is wisest."</note> and therefore must needs know what is fittest and best for us to <orig reg="do">doe</orig>: &amp; to prevent all foolish <orig reg="fears">feares</orig>, or shifts, we are given to understand that he is also All sufficient <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse24">24</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse24" n="24">[Author's note: Genesis 17:1] The Scripture cited by Clinton here discusses the covenant of circumcision, so her note is incorrect. 2 Corinthians 12:9, in which God says, "My grace is sufficient unto thee, for my power is made perfect through weakness" seems more applicable.</note>, &amp; therefore <orig reg="infinitely">infinetely</orig> able to <orig reg="bless">blesse</orig> his <orig reg="own">owne</orig> ordinance, and to afford us <orig reg="means">meanes</orig> in our selves (as <orig reg="continual">continuall</orig> experience confirmeth) toward the observance thereof.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130131">If this (as it ought) bee granted, then how venterous <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse25">25</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse25" n="25">"Venter" has become "venture" in modern spelling, and thus Clinton means "adventurous" in the sense of foolish and rash.</note> are those women that dare venter to do otherwise, and so to refuse, and by refusing to <orig reg="despise">dispise</orig> that order, which the most wise and <orig reg="almighty">allmighty</orig> God hath appointed, and in steed therof to <orig reg="choose">chuse</orig> their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> pleasures?  Oh, what peace can there be to these <orig reg="women's">womens</orig> consciences, <orig reg="unless">unlesse</orig> through the <orig reg="darkness">darknesse</orig> of their understanding they judge it no disobedience?</p><p xml:id="clinton_130132">And then they will drive me to prove that this nursing and nourishing of their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children in their own bosoms is Gods ordinance; they are very <orig reg="willful">willfull</orig>, or very ignorant, if they make a question of it.  For it is proved sufficiently to be their <orig reg="duty">dutie</orig>, both by Gods word, and also by his works.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130134">By his word it is proved, first by <hi rend="italic">Example</hi>, namely the example of <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>. For who sucked her <orig reg="sons">sonnes</orig> Cain, Abel, Seth, &amp;c. but her <orig reg="self">selfe</orig>?  Which <orig reg="she">shee</orig> did not only of meere necessity, because yet not other woman was created; but especially because <orig reg="she">shee</orig> was their mother, and so <orig reg="saw">sawe</orig> it was her duty: and because <orig reg="she">shee</orig> had a true <orig reg="natural">naturall</orig> affection, which moved her to do it gladly. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse26">26</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse26" n="26">Genesis says nothing of Eve's nursing or her happiness at fulfilling her maternal role.</note> Next the example of Sarah the wife of Abraham <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse27">27</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse27" n="27">[Author's note: Genesis 21.7].  The passage reads "And she [Sarah] said, 'Who would have said to Abraham that Sarah would have given children <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>? for I have borne him a <orig reg="son">sonne</orig> in his old age.'"</note>; for <orig reg="she">shee</orig> both gave her <orig reg="son">sonne</orig> Isaac suck, as doing the <orig reg="duty">dutie</orig> commanded of God: And also took great comfort and delight therein, as 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130133" n="8"/>
a duty well pleasing to <orig reg="herself">herselfe</orig>; whence she spake of it, as of an action worthy to be named in holy rejoicing. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse28">28</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse28" n="28">Clinton is referring to Sarah's words in Genesis 21:6, "And Sarah said 'God has made me to <orig reg="rejoice">rejoyce</orig>; all that <orig reg="hear">heare</orig> shall <orig reg="rejoice">rejoyce</orig> with me.'"</note>  Now if <hi rend="italic">Sarah</hi>, so great a <hi rend="italic">Princesse</hi>, did nurse her <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="child">childe</orig>, why should any of us neglect to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> the like, except (which God forbid) we <orig reg="think">thinke</orig><orig reg="scorn">scorne</orig> to follow her, whose daughters it is out glory to be, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse29">29</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse29" n="29">[Author's note: 1 Peter 3:6].  Verses 5 and 6 are applicable: "As Sarah obeyed Abraham, and called him Syr: whose daughters ye are, whiles ye do wel."</note> and which we be only upon this condition, that we imitate her well-doing.  Let us <orig reg="look">looke</orig> therefore to our worthy Pattern, noting withal, that <orig reg="she">shee</orig> put her <orig reg="self">selfe</orig> to <orig reg="work">worke</orig> when she was very old, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse30">30</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse30" n="30">In Genesis 18:17, Sarah is reported to be ninety years old.</note> and so might she better have excused her <orig reg="self">selfe</orig>, then we <orig reg="younger">yonger</orig> women can: being also more able to hire, and <orig reg="keep">keepe</orig> a nurse, then any of us.  But why is <orig reg="she">shee</orig> not followed by most in the practise of this duty?  Even because they want <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse31">31</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse31" n="31">I.e., "Lack."</note> her <orig reg="virtue">vertue</orig> and piety. This want is the common <orig reg="hindrance">hinderance</orig> to this point of the <orig reg="woman's">womans</orig> obedience; for this want makes them want love to Gods precepts, want love to his doctrine, and like step-mothers, want due love to their own children.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130136">But now to another worthy example, namely that excellent woman Hannah, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse32">32</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse32" n="32">[Author's note: 1 Samuel 1:23] The passage reads "Elkanah her husband said unto her, 'Do what seemeth thee best, tary until thou hast weaned him'. . . So the women abode and gave her <orig reg="son">sonne</orig><orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> until she weaned him."</note> who having after much affliction of <orig reg="mind">minde</orig> obtained a <orig reg="son">sonne</orig> of God, whom she vowed unto God, <orig reg="she">shee</orig> did not put him to another to nurse, but nursed him her <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="self">selfe</orig><orig reg="until">untill</orig> she had weaned him, &amp; carried him to be consecrate unto the Lord:  As well knowing that this duty of giving her <orig reg="child">childe</orig><orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>, was acceptable unto God, as for the cause thereof <orig reg="she">shee</orig> did not <orig reg="sin">sinne</orig> in staying with it at home from the yearly sacrifice: but now women, especially of any place, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse33">33</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse33" n="33">I.e., women from the nobility and gentry.</note> and of little grace, <orig reg="do">doe</orig> not 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130135" n="9"/>
hold this duty acceptable to God, because ut us unacceptable to themselves: as if they would have the Lord to like, and dislike, according to their <orig reg="vain">vaine</orig> lusts. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse34">34</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse34" n="34">Clinton is paraphrasing 1 Timothy 3:6 here, which is a discussion of sinful men and women.  It particularly mentions "captive simple women, laden with <orig reg="sins">sinnes</orig>, and led with divers lusts."</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130138">To proceed, take notice of one example more, that is, of the <hi rend="italic">blessed Virgin</hi>: as her womb bare our <hi rend="italic">blessed Savior</hi>, so her pappe gave him <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse35">35</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse35" n="35">See Luke 1:39-2:7 for a narrative of Jesus's birth.  The Scripture does not note Mary's breastfeeding Jesus; however, at the Crucifixion, one of the daughters of Jerusalem cries out "Blessed is the womb that bare thee and the papps thou hast sucked" (Luke 11:27).</note>  Now who shall deny the <orig reg="own">owne</orig> mothers suckling of their own children to bee their duty, since every godly <orig reg="matron">matrone</orig> hath walked in these steps before them: <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>, the mother of al the living, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse36">36</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse36" n="36">Eve is called "mother of all living" in Genesis 3:20.</note> Sarah the mother of al the <orig reg="faithful">faithfull</orig>, <hi rend="italic">Hannah</hi> so <orig reg="graciously">gratiously</orig> heard of God, <hi rend="italic">Mary</hi> blessed among women, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse37">37</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse37" n="37">This appellation appears in Luke 1:42, immediately before the Magnificat, when Elizabeth cries out "Blessed art thou among women because the fruit of thy womb is blessed."</note> and called blessed of al ages.  And who can say but that the rest of holy women mentioned in the holy Scriptures did the like, since no doubt the speech of that noble dame, saying, who would have said to <hi rend="italic">Abraham</hi> that Sarah should have given children <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>? <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse38">38</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse38" n="38">[Author's note: Genesis 21:7] See Note 27 for the Scripture.</note> was taken from the ordinary <orig reg="custom">custome</orig> of mothers in those <orig reg="less">lesse</orig> corrupted times. And so much for <orig reg="proof">proofe</orig> of this office, and duty to Gods ordinance, by his own <hi rend="italic">Word</hi> according to the argument of <hi rend="italic">Examples</hi>: I hope I shall likewise prove it by the same word from <orig reg="plain">plaine</orig><hi rend="italic">Precepts</hi><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse39">39</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse39" n="39">[Author's note: 1 Timothy 5:14] The "<orig reg="plain">plaine</orig> Precepts" Clinton refers to concern women's roles: "I <orig reg="will">wil</orig> therefore that younger women <orig reg="marry">marie</orig>, and <orig reg="bear">beare</orig> children, &amp; govern the house, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> give none occasion to the <orig reg="adversary">adversarie</orig> to <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> evill."</note>.  First from that <hi rend="italic">Precept</hi>, which willeth the younger women to marry, and to <hi rend="italic">Beare</hi> children, that is, not only to <hi rend="italic">Beare</hi> them in the <orig reg="womb">wombe</orig>, and to bring the forth, but also to <hi rend="italic">Beare</hi> them on their knee, in their <orig reg="arms">armes</orig>, and at their breasts <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse40">40</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse40" n="40">[Author's note: Ver. 10] She references the reader to 1 Timothy 5:10, which states, regarding a widow's virtue "And <orig reg="well">wel</orig> reported of for good <orig reg="works">workes</orig> if she hath nourished her children."</note>: for this <hi rend="italic">Bearing</hi> a little before is called nourishing, and bringing up: and to <orig reg="enforce">inforce</orig> it the better upon <orig reg="women's">womens</orig><pb xml:id="clinton_130137" n="10"/>
consciences, it is numbered first of the good <orig reg="works">workes</orig> for which godly women should be well-reported of.  And well it may be the first, because if holy Ministers, or other Christians <orig reg="do">doe</orig><orig reg="hear">heare</orig> of a good woman to be brought to bed, and her child to be living, their first questions usually is, whether she her <orig reg="self">selfe</orig> give it <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>, yea or no?  if the <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> be she doth, then they commend her: if the <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> be she doth not, they are sorry for her. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse41">41</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse41" n="41">This anecdotal evidence of a social practice does not occur in the Bible, nor do any of the Puritan treatises (Gouge, Dod and Clever) mention it.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130139">And thus I come to a second <hi rend="italic">Precept</hi>.  I pray you, who that judges aright; doth not hold the suckling of her <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="child">childe</orig> the part of a true mother, of an honest mother, of a just mother, of a <orig reg="sincere">syncere</orig> mother, of a mother worthy of love, of a mother deserving of good report, of a <orig reg="virtuous">vertuous</orig> mother, of a mother winning praise for it? <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse42">42</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse42" n="42">Clinton makes this passage gender and role specific, modeling it on Philippians 4:8, "Furthermore, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honest, whatsoever, things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are pertinent to love, whatsoever things are of good report, if there be <orig reg="any">anie</orig><orig reg="virtue">vertue</orig>, or if there be <orig reg="any">anie</orig> praise, <orig reg="think">thinke</orig> on these things."</note>  All this is assented to by any of good understanding. Therefore this is also a <hi rend="italic">Precept</hi>, as for other duties, so for <hi rend="italic">This</hi> of mothers to their children, which saith, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse43">43</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse43" n="43">[Author's note: Philippians 4:8.] See Note 45.</note> what soever things are true, whatsoever things are honest, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are worthy of love, whatsoever things be of good report, if there be any <orig reg="virtue">vertue</orig>, if there be any praise, <orig reg="think">thinke</orig> on these things, these things do and the God of peace shall be with you.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130141">So <orig reg="far">farre</orig> for my promise, to prove by the word of God, that it is his ordinance that women should nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children: now I will endeavour to prove it by his <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="works">workes</orig></hi>: First by his <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="works">workes</orig> of judgement</hi>; if it were not his ordinance for mothers to give their children <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>, it were no <hi rend="italic">judgement</hi> to bereave them of their <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, but it is specified to be a great <hi rend="italic">judgement</hi> to bereave them thereof, &amp; to give them dry breasts, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse44">44</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse44" n="44">This is the curse of the Israelites against their captors: "O Lord, give them; what wilt thou give them?  give them a barren <orig reg="womb">wombe</orig> &amp; dry breast" (Hosea 9:14).</note> therefore it is to be gathered, even from hence, that it is his ordinance, since to deprive them of <orig reg="means">meanes</orig> to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> it, is a punishment of them.
<pb xml:id="clinton_130140" n="11"/></p><p xml:id="clinton_130142">I <orig reg="add">adde</orig> to this <hi rend="italic">the <orig reg="work">worke</orig> that God worketh in the very nature of mothers</hi>, which proveth also that he hath ordained that they should nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children: for by his secret operation on the mothers affection is so knit by natures law to her tender babe, as she <orig reg="finds">findes</orig> no power to deny to suckle it, no not when she is in hazard to lose her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> life, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse45">45</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse45" n="45">See <title>The Autobiography of Alice Thornton</title> (ed. Charles Jackson.  Surtees Society, 1875), 92 for a vivid illustration of this.  Thornton, suffering from almost a year's post-partum weakness after her daughter Betty's birth, worries that the cries of her ill older daughter Alice will "lessen my milk" and rejoices when, two weeks later, she recovers and is "overjoyed to give my <orig reg="sweet">sweete</orig> Betty <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>."</note> by attending on it, for in such a case it is not said, let the mother fly, and leave her infant to the <orig reg="peril">perill</orig>, as if she were dispensed with: but only it is said <hi rend="italic">woe to her</hi>.  As if she were to be pitied, that for nature to her child, she must be <orig reg="unnatural">unnaturall</orig> to her <orig reg="self">selfe</orig>: now if any then being even at liberty, and in peace, with all plenty, shall deny to give <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> to their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children, they <orig reg="go">goe</orig> against nature: and shew that God hath not done so much for them <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse46">46</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse46" n="46">[Author's note: Lamentations 7:3] There is no chapter 7 in Lamentations, thus Clinton's (or the printer's) reference is in error.  See Note 47 for the applicable passage.</note> as to <orig reg="work">worke</orig> in any good, no not in their nature, but left them more savage then the Dragons, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse47">47</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse47" n="47">See Lamentations 4:3, "Even the dragons <orig reg="draw">drawe</orig> out the breasts &amp; give <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> to their <orig reg="young">yong</orig>, but the daughters of my people is become <orig reg="cruel">cruell</orig> like ye ostriches in the wildernes."</note> and as <orig reg="cruel">cruell</orig> to their little ones as the Ostriches. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse48">48</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse48" n="48">Clinton here paraphrases Job 39:16-19 as well as the Lamentations passage above, where the ostrich is berated because he "sheweth himselfe <orig reg="cruel">cruell</orig> unto his <orig reg="young">yong</orig> ones, as they were not his, and is without <orig reg="fear">feare</orig>, as if he had travailed in vain."  The gloss to the passage adds that the bird is "without <orig reg="natural">naturall</orig> affection toward his <orig reg="young">yong</orig>," i.e., precisely Clinton's argument.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130144">Now another <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="work">worke</orig></hi> of God, proving this point is the <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="work">worke</orig> of his provision</hi>, for every <orig reg="kind">kinde</orig> to be apt, and able to nourish their own fruit: there is no beast that feeds their young with <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, but the Lord, even from the first ground of the order of nature, <hi rend="italic">Growe and <orig reg="multiply">multiplie</orig></hi>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse49">49</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse49" n="49">Part of the Israelites covenant with God is that "he will love thee and <orig reg="bless">blesse</orig> thee, &amp; <orig reg="multiply">multiplie</orig> thee: he will also <orig reg="bless">blesse</orig> the <orig reg="fruit">frute</orig> of thy <orig reg="womb">wombe</orig>" (Deuteronomy 7:13).</note> hath provided it of <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> to suckle their own young, which every beast takes so naturally unto, as if another beast come forward to offer the office of a Damme unto it, they show according to their fashion, a <orig reg="plain">plaine</orig> dislike of it: as if nature did <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> in them, and say it is contrary to Gods order in nature, commanding each <orig reg="kind">kinde</orig> to increase, and <orig reg="multiply">multiplie</orig> in their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> bodies, and by 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130143" n="12"/>
their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> breasts, not to bring forth by one Damme, and to bring up by another: <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse50">50</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse50" n="50">Gouge's <title>Of Domesticall Duties</title> states that God "hath made it a matter of impossibility for women to <orig reg="bear">beare</orig> and bring forth their children by another" (L12v).</note> but it is his ordinance that every <orig reg="kind">kinde</orig> should both bring forth, and also nourish its <orig reg="own">owne</orig> fruit.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130145">Much more should this work of God <orig reg="prevail">prevaile</orig> to <orig reg="persuade">purswade</orig> women, made as man in the image of God, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse51">51</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse51" n="51">This is the description of man from Genesis 1:26, "Let us make man in our own image."</note> and therefore should be ashamed to be put to <orig reg="school">schoole</orig> to <orig reg="learn">learne</orig> good nature of the unreasonable creature.  In us also, as we <orig reg="know">knowe</orig> by experience, God provideth <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> in our breasts against the time of our <orig reg="children's">childrens</orig> birth, and this he has done ever since it was said to us also, <hi rend="italic">Increase and multiply</hi>, so that this <orig reg="work">worke</orig> of his provision sheweth that <orig reg="he">hee</orig> tieth us likewise to nourish the children of our <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="womb">wombe</orig>, with our <orig reg="own">owne</orig> breasts even by the order of nature: yea, it sheweth that he so careth for, and regardeth little children even from the <orig reg="womb">wombe</orig>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse52">52</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse52" n="52">Perhaps an oblique reference to Psalm 127:3, "Behold children are the inheritance of the Lord, and the <orig reg="fruit">frute</orig> of the <orig reg="womb">wombe</orig> his reward."</note> that he would have them nursed by those that in all reason will <orig reg="look">looke</orig> to them with the kindest affection, namely their mothers; &amp; in giving them <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> for it, <orig reg="he">hee</orig> doth plainly tell them that he requires it.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130147">Oh consider, how comes our <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>? <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse53">53</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse53" n="53">Compare Clinton's religious emphasis with the ancient medical ones discussed in Thomas Lacquer's  <title>Making Sex: The Body and Gender from the Greeks to Freud</title> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press,1990) where breast milk is viewed as a refined form of menstrual blood.  See also Gail Kern Paster's <title>The Body Embarrassed: Drama and the Disciplines of Shame in Early Modern England</title> (Cornell: Cornell University Press, 1993), especially Chapters 4 and 5 for a discussion of nursing and humoral theory.</note>  is it not by the direct providence of God?  Why provides he it, but for the child?  The Mothers then that refuse to nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children, <orig reg="do">doe</orig> they not despise Gods providence?  Doe they not deny Gods will?  Doe they not as it were say, <hi rend="italic">I see, O God, by the <orig reg="means">meanes</orig> thou hast put in to me, that thou wouldst have me nurse this child thou hast given me but I will not <orig reg="do">doe</orig> so much for thee</hi>.  Oh impious, and impudent unthankfullnesse; yea monstrous <orig reg="unnaturalness">unnaturalnesse</orig>, both to their own natural fruit borne so <orig reg="near">neare</orig> their breasts, and fed in their <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="wombs">wombes</orig>, and yet may not be suffered to <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> their <orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="milk">milke</orig>.
<pb xml:id="clinton_130146" n="13"/></p><p xml:id="clinton_130148">And this unthankfullnesse, and <orig reg="unnaturalness">unnaturalnesse</orig> is <orig reg="oftener">oftner</orig> the <orig reg="sin">sinne</orig> of the <hi rend="italic">Higher</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">richer sort</hi> then of the meaner and the poorer, except some nice <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse54">54</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse54" n="54">"Nice" in the sense of overly precise, foolish, wanton, fastidious. (OED).</note> and <orig reg="proud">prowd</orig> idle dames, who will imitate their betters, till they make their <orig reg="poor">poore</orig> husbands beggars.  And this is one hurt which the better <orig reg="rank">ranke</orig><orig reg="do">doe</orig> by their ill example, egge, and <orig reg="embolden">imbolden</orig> the lower ones to follow them in their <orig reg="loss">losse</orig>: were it not better for <hi rend="italic">Us greater persons</hi> to <orig reg="keep">keepe</orig> Gods ordinance, &amp; to shew the meaner their <orig reg="duty">dutie</orig> in our good example?  I am sure wee have more <orig reg="helps">helpes</orig> to <orig reg="perform">performe</orig> it, and have fewer probable reasons to allege against it, then women that live by hard labour, &amp; <orig reg="painful">painfull</orig> toile. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse55">55</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse55" n="55">The economic issues involved with maternal versus wet nursing are well-documented in both Renaissance sources and modern historiography.  See Valerie Fildes's <title>Wet Nursing: A History from Antiquity to the Present</title> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1988), Chapters 4-6 for a thorough summary.</note>  If such mothers as refuse this office of love, &amp; nature to their children, should hereafter be refused, despised, and neglected of those their children, were they not justly requited according to their unkind dealing?  I might say more in handling this first point of my promise, but I leave the larger, and learneder discourse hereof unto men of art, and learning: only I <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> of so much as I <orig reg="read">reade</orig>, and <orig reg="know">knowe</orig> in my <orig reg="own">owne</orig> experience, which if any of my <orig reg="sex">sexe</orig>, and condition do <orig reg="receive">receave</orig> good by, I am glad: if they <orig reg="scorn">scorne</orig> it, they shall have the reward of scorners.  I write in <orig reg="modesty">modestie</orig>, and can <orig reg="reap">reape</orig> no disgrace by their immodest folly. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse56">56</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse56" n="56">The most obvious connection of writing, which is tantamount to public speech, and immodesty appears in 1 Timothy 2:11-12, "Let the woman <orig reg="learn">learne</orig> in silence with all subjection.  I permit not a woman to <orig reg="teach">teache</orig>, nether to <orig reg="usurp">usurpe</orig><orig reg="authority">authorite</orig> over a man, but to be in silence."</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130149">And so I come to the last part of my promise, which is to <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> objections made by divers <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse57">57</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse57" n="57">I.e.,  diverse or many.</note> against this duty of mothers to their children.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130151">First it is objected that <hi rend="italic">Rebeckah</hi> had a nurse, and that therefore her mother did not give her <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> of her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> breasts, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse58">58</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse58" n="58">There is no direct narrative of Rebeckah's childhood in Genesis.  She first appears, apparently an adolescent accompanied by servants, as a prospective wife for Isaac. See Note 61.</note> and so good women, in the first ages, did not hold them to this office of nursing their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children. To this I answer, that if her mother had <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, and health, 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130150" n="14"/>
and yet did not put this duty from her to another, it was her fault, &amp; so proveth nothing against me. But it is manifest that she that <hi rend="italic">Rebeckah</hi> calleth her nurse, was called so, either for that she most tended her while her mother suckled her: or for that she weaned her: or for that during her nonage, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse59">59</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse59" n="59">I.e.,  legal infancy or youth.</note> and childhood, <orig reg="she">shee</orig> did minister to her continually such good things as delighted, and nourished her up.  For to any one of these the name of a <orig reg="nurse">nourse</orig> is fitly given; whence a good wife is called her husbands <orig reg="nurse">nourse</orig>: and that <hi rend="italic">Rebeckahs</hi><orig reg="nurse">nourse</orig><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse60">60</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse60" n="60">[Author's note: Genesis 24:61]  Clinton's version is almost an exact quotation: "Then Rebeckah arose, and her <orig reg="maids">maides</orig>."</note> was only such a one, appeareth, because afterward she is not named a <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="nurse">nourse</orig></hi>, but a <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="maid">maide</orig></hi>, saying: Then <hi rend="italic">Rebeckah</hi> rose and her <orig reg="maids">maides</orig>, now <orig reg="maids">maides</orig> give not suck out of their breasts, never any virgin, or honest <orig reg="maid">maide</orig><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse61">61</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse61" n="61">Clinton expressly conflates the meaning of maid as both servant and virgin here to serve her argument.</note> gave suck, but that <hi rend="italic">blessed one</hi> from an extraordinary &amp; blessed power. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse62">62</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse62" n="62">I.e.,  The Virgin Mary.</note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130153">Secondly it is objected, that it is troublesome; that it is <orig reg="noisome">noysome</orig><ref target="#clinton.015.countesse63">63</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse63" n="63">"Noisome" means both harmful or offensive and ill-smelling (OED).</note> to ones clothes; that it makes one <orig reg="look">looke</orig> old, &amp;c. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse64">64</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse64" n="64">These objections are also raised and refuted in Erasmus's "'The Woman in Childbed" (<title>Colloquies</title>.  London: 1671) V2r, Dod and Clever's <title>A Godly Forme of Household Government</title> (London: 1612) O2r, and in Gouge's <title>Of Domesticall Duties</title> (London: 1622) L12r.</note>  All such reasons are uncomely, and unchristian to be objected: and therefore unworthy to be answered, they argue <hi rend="italic">unmotherly affection, <orig reg="idleness">idlenesse</orig>, desire to have liberty to gadd from home, pride, fool finesse, lust <orig reg="wantonness">wantonnesse</orig></hi>, &amp; the like <orig reg="evils">evills</orig>.  <orig reg="Ask">Aske</orig><hi rend="italic">Sarah, Hannah</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">blessed Virgin</hi>, and any modest loving mother, what trouble they accounted it to give their little ones <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>?  behold most nursing mothers, and they be as <orig reg="clean">cleane</orig> and sweet in their <orig reg="clothes">cloathes</orig>, and carry their age, and hold their <orig reg="beauty">beautie</orig>, as well as those that suckle not and most likely are they so to <orig reg="do">doe</orig>, because keeping God's <hi rend="italic">Ordinance</hi>, they are sure of Gods <hi rend="italic">Blessing</hi>: and it hath <orig reg="been">beene</orig> observed in some women that they grew more <orig reg="beautiful">beautifull</orig>, and better favoured, by very nursing their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children.
<pb xml:id="clinton_130152" n="15"/></p><p xml:id="clinton_130154">But there are some women that object <orig reg="fear">feare</orig>; saying that they are so <orig reg="weak">weake</orig>, &amp; so tender, that they are afraid to venter to give their children <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>, least they <orig reg="endanger">indanger</orig> their health thereby. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse65">65</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse65" n="65">See Fildes's <title>Wet Nursing</title> (London: Basil Blackwell, 1988), 88-90 for a discussion of women's fears about nursing.</note>  Of these, I demand, why then they did venter to marry, and so to <orig reg="bear">beare</orig> children, and if they say they could not <orig reg="choose">chuse</orig>, and that they thought not that marriage would <orig reg="impair">impaire</orig> their health, I <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> that for the same reasons should they set themselves to nurse their <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children, because they should not <orig reg="choose">chuse</orig> but <orig reg="do">doe</orig> what God would have them to <orig reg="do">doe</orig>: and they should <orig reg="believe">beleeve</orig> that this <orig reg="work">worke</orig> will be for their health also, seeing it is ordinary with the Lord to give <hi rend="italic">good <orig reg="Stomach">Stomache</orig>, health, and strength</hi> to almost all mothers that take this <orig reg="pains">paines</orig> with their children. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse66">66</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse66" n="66">What Clinton phrases as a commonplace has not been located in midwifery treatises; Gouge, however, does employ the phrase "The drawing forth of a <orig reg="woman's">womans</orig><orig reg="milk">milke</orig> by her <orig reg="child">childe</orig> is a means to get and preserve a good stomach, which is a great preservative of good health" (<title>Of Domesticall Duties</title>, L12r). </note></p><p xml:id="clinton_130155">One <orig reg="answer">answere</orig> more to all the objections that use to be made against giving children <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig>, is this, that now the hardness, to effect this matter, is much <orig reg="removed">remooved</orig> by a late example of a <hi rend="bold">tender young Lady</hi>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse67">67</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse67" n="67">It is unknown whether Clinton meant a specific unnamed woman or her daughter-in-law Briget.</note> and you may all be encouraged to follow after, in that wherein she hath gone before you, &amp; so made the way more <orig reg="easy">easie</orig>, and more <orig reg="hopeful">hopefull</orig> by that which <orig reg="she">shee</orig> findeth possible and comfortable by Gods blessing, and no offense to her Lord nor her <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="self">selfe</orig></hi>: she might have had as many doubts, and lets, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse68">68</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse68" n="68">I.e.,  hindrances or obstructions (OED).</note> as any of you, but she was willing to try how God would enable her, &amp; he hath given her good <orig reg="success">successe</orig>, as I hope he will <orig reg="do">doe</orig> to others that are willing to trust in God for his <orig reg="help">helpe</orig>.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130157">Now if any reading these few lines <orig reg="return">returne</orig> against me, that it may bee I my <orig reg="self">selfe</orig> have given my own children suck: &amp; therefore am bolder, and more <orig reg="busy">busie</orig> to meddle in urging this point, to the end to insult over, &amp; to make them bee blamed that have not done it.  I answer, that whether I have, or have not performed this my bounden duty, I will not deny to tell my <orig reg="own">owne</orig><pb xml:id="clinton_130156" n="16"/>
practise.  I <orig reg="know">knowe</orig> &amp; acknowledge that I should have done it; it was not for want of will in my <orig reg="self">selfe</orig>, but <hi rend="italic">partly that I was overruled by <orig reg="another's">anothers</orig> authority</hi>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse69">69</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse69" n="69">This biographical information is vague, but it is likely that Clinton means her husband, who would have objected to abstaining from sexual relations with his wife while she lactated, so that she produce as many children as possible for heirs.  See Valerie Fildes <title>Breasts, Bottles and Babies</title> (Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh Press, 1986) 152-210.  She may also be referring to her mother-in-law, with whom she resided; because Clinton was only ten when she married and fifteen at the birth of her first child, the older woman likely had significant influence on her youthful daughter-in-law.</note> and partly deceived by some ill <orig reg="counsel">counsell</orig>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">partly I had not considered so well of my duty in this motherly office</hi>, as since I did when it was too late for me to put it into execution.  Wherefore being pricked in hart <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse70">70</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse70" n="70">See Acts 2:37, "Now when they heard it, they were pricked in their hearts and said unto Peter and the others, 'Brethren, what <orig reg="shall">shal</orig> we do?'"</note> for my undutifullnesse, this way I study to <orig reg="redeem">redeeme</orig> my peace, first by <hi rend="italic">repentance</hi> towards God, humbly and often craving his pardon for this my offence: secondly by <hi rend="italic">studying how to shew double love to my children</hi> to make them amends for neglect of this part of love to them, when they should have hung on my breasts, &amp; have been nourished in mine <orig reg="own">owne</orig> bosome: thirdly <hi rend="italic">by doing my endeavour to prevent many christian mothers</hi> from <orig reg="sinning">sining</orig> in the same <orig reg="kind">kinde</orig>, against our most loving and <orig reg="gracious">gratious</orig> God.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130159">And for this cause I add unto my performed promise, this short exhortation: namely I beseech all godly women to remember, how we <hi rend="italic">elder</hi> ones are commanded to instruct the <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="younger">yonger</orig></hi>, to love their children, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse71">71</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse71" n="71">See Titus 2:3-4, "The Elder women, likewise, that they be in such behavior that becometh holiness . . . . That they may instruct the younger that they love their husbands, that they love their children."</note> now therefore love them so as to do this office unto them when they are borne, more gladly for <hi rend="italic">love</hi> sake, then a <hi rend="italic">stranger</hi>, who bore them not, shall do for <hi rend="italic">lucre</hi> sake, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse72">72</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse72" n="72">The Biblical scorn for "filthy lucre" is recorded in 1 Timothy 3:3, Titus 1:7, and 1 Peter 5:2.</note> Also I pray you to set no more so light by Gods blessing in your <orig reg="own">owne</orig> breasts, which the holy Spirit ranketh with other excellent blessings, if it be <orig reg="unlawful">unlawfull</orig> to trample underfeet a cluster of grapes, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse73">73</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse73" n="73">See Numbers 13:24, "when they cut <orig reg="down">downe</orig> a branch with on cluster of grapes, and they bare it between two. . . . "</note> in which a little wine is found; then how <orig reg="unlawful">unlawfull</orig> is it to <orig reg="destroy">destroye</orig> and <orig reg="dry">drie</orig> up those breasts, in which your <orig reg="own">owne</orig> child (and perhaps Gods very elect, to whom to be a nourishing 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130158" n="17"/>
father, is a Kings honour; and to whom to be a nourishing mother, is a Queens honour) <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse74">74</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse74" n="74">The phrase "nursing father" appears in Numbers 11:12, but the specific reference here is Isaiah 49:23, "And Kings shall be thy nursing fathers and Queens <orig reg="shall">shal</orig> be thy <orig reg="nurses">nourses</orig>. . . ."</note> might <orig reg="find">finde</orig> food of <orig reg="sincere">syncere</orig><orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse75">75</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse75" n="75">See Note 8 for the Scriptural reference here.</note> even from Gods immediate providence, <orig reg="until">untill</orig> it were fitter for stronger meat? <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse76">76</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse76" n="76">Clinton condenses and cleverly applies a series of verses from Hebrews 5: 12-14 here: ". . . yet have ye <orig reg="need">nede</orig><orig reg="again">againe</orig> yet we <orig reg="teach">teche</orig> you the first principles of the <orig reg="word">worde</orig> of God: and are become <orig reg="such">suche</orig> as have need of <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, and not of strong meat.  For every one that useth <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, is inexperte in the <orig reg="word">worde</orig> of righteousnesse, for he is a babe.  But strong meat belongeth to them that are of age, which through long custom have their <orig reg="wits">wittes</orig> exercised, to <orig reg="discern">discerne</orig> both good and evil."</note>  I <orig reg="do">doe</orig><orig reg="know">knowe</orig> that the Lord may deny some women, either to have any <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> in their breasts at all, or to have any passage for their <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, or to have any health. or to have a right <orig reg="mind">minde</orig> so that they may be letted from this duty, by <hi rend="italic">want</hi>, by <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="sickness">sicknesse</orig></hi>, by <hi rend="italic">lunacy</hi>, &amp;c. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse77">77</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse77" n="77">All the Puritan writers who address the subject of breastfeeding do allow for exceptions in the case of extreme ill-health or madness.  See Fildes' <title>Breasts, Bottles, and Babies</title> 406-407 for statistics regarding exceptions.</note>  But I <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> not to these: I <orig reg="speak">speake</orig> to you, whose <hi rend="italic">consciences</hi> witness against you, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse78">78</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse78" n="78">See Romans 2:15 and 9:1 for the use of the phrase "consciences bearing witness."</note> that you cannot justly <orig reg="allege">alleage</orig> any of those impediments.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130161">Doe you submit your selves, to the <orig reg="pain">paine</orig> and trouble of this ordinance of God? trust not other women, whom <hi rend="italic">wages <orig reg="hires">hyres</orig></hi> to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> it, better then your selves, whom God, <hi rend="italic">and nature ties</hi> to do it. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse79">79</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse79" n="79">See the seventeenth-century proverbial expression about the greed of wet nurses, "Nurses put one bit in the child's mouth and two in their own" (<title>Dictionary of 16th and 17th Century Proverbs</title>, ed. Morris Palmer Tilley).</note>  I have found by grievous experience, such dissembling in nurses, pretending sufficiency of <orig reg="milk">milke</orig>, when indeed they had too much <orig reg="scarcity">scarcitie</orig>; pretending <orig reg="willingness">willingnesse</orig>, towardnesse, <orig reg="wakefullness">wakefullnesse</orig>, when indeed they had been most <orig reg="willful">wilfull</orig>, most froward, and most <orig reg="slothful">slothfull</orig>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse80">80</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse80" n="80">The catalogue of a nurse's faults is a standard part of this genre.  See Fildes <title>Babies, Breasts and Bottles</title> 168-184 and <title>Wet Nursing</title> 79-100 for a survey of these faults in both moral and medical tracts.</note> as I <orig reg="fear">feare</orig> the death of one or two of my little Babes came by the <orig reg="default">defalt</orig> of their nurses.  Of all those which I had for <orig reg="eighteen">eighteene</orig> children, I had but two which were but throughly willing, and <orig reg="careful">carefull</orig>: divers have had their children miscarry in the nurses hands, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse81">81</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse81" n="81">Infant mortality among nurslings was especially high due to the delay in feeding while a nurse was found, the lack of specific trans-placental immunity, and to "overlaying."  See Fildes' <title>Wet-Nursing</title> 90-100.</note> and are such mothers (if it were by 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130160" n="18"/>
the nurses <orig reg="carelessness">carelessnesse</orig>) guiltless?  I know not how they should, since they will shut them out of the <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="arms">armes</orig> of nature</hi>, and leave them to the will of a <hi rend="italic">stranger</hi>; yea to one that will <orig reg="seem">seeme</orig> to <hi rend="italic">estrange</hi> her <orig reg="self">selfe</orig> from her <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="child">childe</orig></hi>, to give <orig reg="suck">sucke</orig> to the <hi rend="bold">nurse-child</hi>.  This she may <orig reg="fain">faine</orig> to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> upon a <hi rend="italic">covetous composition</hi>, but she frets at it in her <orig reg="mind">minde</orig>, if she have nay <orig reg="natural">naturall</orig> affection.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130162">Therefore be no longer at the trouble, and at the care to hire others to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> your <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="own">owne</orig><orig reg="work">worke</orig></hi>: bee not so <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="unnatural">unnaturall</orig></hi> to thrust away your <orig reg="own">owne</orig> children: be not so <hi rend="italic">hardy</hi> as to venter a <hi rend="italic">tender Babe</hi> to a <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="less">lesse</orig> tender heart</hi>: bee not <hi rend="italic">accessary</hi> to that disorder of causing a <hi rend="italic">poorer woman to banish her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> infant</hi>, for the entertaining of a <hi rend="italic">richer <orig reg="woman's">womans</orig> child</hi>, as it were, bidding her <hi rend="italic">unlove her <orig reg="own">owne</orig> to love yours</hi>. <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse82">82</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse82" n="82">See Gouge's <title>Of Domesticall Duties</title>, "For who are commonly chosen as nurses? even <orig reg="poor">poore</orig> simple <orig reg="country">countrie</orig> women which have <orig reg="much">muche</orig><orig reg="work">worke</orig> to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> and little <orig reg="help">helpe</orig>, and so are forced to let their children lie and <orig reg="cry">crie</orig>, many times til it burst again" (L1v).</note>  Wee have followed <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi> in transgression, let us follow her in obedience.  When God laid the <orig reg="sorrows">sorrowes</orig> of conception, of breeding of bringing forth and of bringing up her children upon her, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse83">83</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse83" n="83">See Genesis 3:16 for Eve's burden: "I <orig reg="will">wil</orig> greatly increase thy sorrows &amp; thy conceptions.  In <orig reg="sorrow">sorow</orig> thou shalt bring forth children. . . ."</note> &amp; so upon us in her <orig reg="loins">loynes</orig>, did <orig reg="she">shee</orig> reply any word against?  Not a word; so I pray you all mine <orig reg="own">owne</orig><hi rend="italic">Daughters</hi>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse84">84</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse84" n="84">Clinton refers to her six grown daughters here.  See Mary R. Mahl and Helene Koon, <title>The Female Spectator: English Women Writers Before 1800</title> (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1977) 88-89.</note> and others that are still child-bearing reply not against the duty of suckling them, when God hath sent you them.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130164">Indeed I see some, if the <orig reg="weather">wether</orig> be wet, or cold; if they way be <orig reg="foul">fowle</orig>; if the Church be far off, I see they are so coy, so nice, so <orig reg="lukewarm">lukewarme</orig>, they will not take <orig reg="pains">paines</orig> for their <hi rend="italic">own <orig reg="souls">soules</orig></hi>. alas, no <orig reg="marvel">marvell</orig> if these will not bee at trouble, and <orig reg="pain">paine</orig>, to nourish their <hi rend="italic"><orig reg="children's">childrens</orig> bodies</hi>, but <orig reg="fear">feare</orig> God, bee diligent to serve him; <orig reg="approve">approove</orig> all his ordinances; <orig reg="seek">seeke</orig> to please him; account it no trouble, or <orig reg="pain">paine</orig> to do any thing that hath the promise of his blessing; and then you will, no doubt, <orig reg="do">doe</orig> this <hi rend="italic">good, laudable, <orig reg="natural">naturall</orig>, loving duty</hi> to your children.  If yet you be not satisfied, 
<pb xml:id="clinton_130163" n="19"/>
inquire not of those that refuse to <orig reg="do">doe</orig> this: consult not with your <orig reg="own">owne</orig> conceit; advise not with flatterers: but <orig reg="ask">aske</orig> the <orig reg="counsel">counsell</orig> of sincere, and <orig reg="faithful">faithfull</orig> Preachers.  If you be satisfied; then take this with you, to make you do it <orig reg="cheerfully">cheerefully</orig>.  <orig reg="Think">Thinke</orig> always, having the child at your breast, and having it in your arms, you have <hi rend="italic">Gods blessing</hi> there.  For children are Gods blessings.  <orig reg="Think">Thinke</orig><orig reg="again">againe</orig> how your Babe crying for your breast, sucking <orig reg="heartily">hartily</orig> the <orig reg="milk">milke</orig> out of it, and growing by it, is the <hi rend="italic">Lords <orig reg="own">owne</orig> instruction</hi>, every <orig reg="hour">houre</orig>, and every day, that you are sucking it, instructing you to shew that you are his <hi rend="italic">new borne Babes</hi>, <ref target="#clinton.015.countesse85">85</ref><note xml:id="clinton.015.countesse85" n="85">See Note 6 for the text of this Scripture from 1 Peter 2:2.</note> by your earnest desire after his word, &amp; the sincere doctrine thereof, and by your daily growing in grace and <orig reg="goodness">goodnesse</orig> thereby, so shall you <orig reg="reap">reape</orig> pleasure, and profit. <orig reg="Again">Againe</orig>, you may consider, that when your <orig reg="child">childe</orig> is at your breast, it is a fit occasion to move your heart to pray for a blessing on that <orig reg="work">worke</orig>; and to give thanks for your child, and ability &amp; freedom unto that, which many a mother would have done and could not; who have tried and ventured their health, &amp; taken much <orig reg="pains">paines</orig>, and yet have not obtained their desire. But they that are fitted every way for this <hi rend="italic">commendable act</hi>, have certainly great cause to be <orig reg="thankful">thankfull</orig>: and I desire that God may have glory and praise for every good <orig reg="work">worke</orig>, and you much comfort, that <orig reg="do">doe</orig><orig reg="seek">seeke</orig> to honour God in all things.  Amen.</p><p xml:id="clinton_130165">FINIS</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>