<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="adair_1308"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Tahlequah, an electronic edition</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Adair, Lena Harnage</reg><orig>Lena Harnage Adair</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Beck Center</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>15kb</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability status="unknown"><p xml:id="adair_1301">1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to
	       download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute
               or display the contributions to the work claimed by
               Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
               provided this header is included in its entirety.  For
               inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Emory
               Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center
               for Electronic collections and services, Emory
               University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>1996</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/179gc</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Adair, Lena Harnage. "Tahlequah."<publisher>Tahlequah Arrow</publisher> Feb. 19, <date>1916</date>: 1-4.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="adair_1302">This text is produced in conjunction with the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Native American</rs><rs type="language">English</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Native American</rs><rs type="form">Unedited</rs><rs type="genre">Poetry</rs><rs type="geography">United States</rs><date>1900-1999</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list type="simple"><item>Tahlequah (Okla.).</item><item>American literature--20th Century--Fiction.</item><item>Women authors, American--20th Century.</item><item>Race relations.</item><item>Native Americans.</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Anna Engle</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change><change><date>2006</date><label>Staff</label><name>Alden Mahler</name>TEI header elements changed to conform to new Beck
	    Center standards.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="adair_1307"><body xml:id="adair_1306"><div xml:id="adair_001" type="poem"><head>Tahlequah</head><pb xml:id="adair_1303" n="1"/><lg type="stanza"><l n="1">Here's to Tahlequah with her wooded hills,</l><l>Her sparkling springs and tinkling rills,</l><l>Her rocky cliffs by ferns o'ergrown,</l><l>And her shady nooks by lovers known:</l><l>Her maidens fair and cultured dames,</l><l>And gifted sons of illustrious names.</l><l>He who drinks of the waters of these lipid [sic] springs;</l><l>Though far he may wander fond memory brings</l><l>Sweet thoughts of the village taat [sic] nestles serene,</l><l>So tranquil and lovely like an enchanted scene;</l><l>Visions of beauty he long will retain,</l><l>And in dreams will he oft visit Tahlequah again.</l><l>About her foothills of the Ozark rise,</l><l>Like a gem surrounded by her setting she lies,</l><l>Near by flows the Illinois-a srystal [sic] stream,</l><l>Brightly the waters o'er its pebbly bed gleam.</l><l>He who loves the beautiful, along its banks may find</l><l>Many a picturesque spot to delight the mind.</l><l>You should see Tahlequah in the month of May,</l><l>When nature has dooned [sic] her brightest array,</l><l>When incense, borne by the perfumed breeze,</l><l>That blows through the snow-white locust trees,</l><l>Around the quaint old capital square,</l><l>Floats out upon the warm sweet air;</l><l>When the emerald sward is bedecked wtih [sic] flowers</l><l>And the birds sing in their leafy bowers,</l><pb xml:id="adair_1304" n="4"/><l>And the voice of the school children on the street,</l><l>Fall [sic] upon the ear like music sweet.</l><l>Many a Tahlequah family its lineage traces</l><l>Back to old England's proudest races,</l><l>For many a noble, to hide his head,</l><l>In Cromwell's time, to America fled,</l><l>And by the Cherokees were made welcome</l><l>To dwell with them in their forest home.</l><l>And in the days when revolutionary strife</l><l>Often endangered the royalists [sic] life,</l><l>Over the mountains of Tennessee,</l><l>The Tory came to dwell with the Cherokee:</l><l>For during that period the Indians were loyal</l><l>To the British crown and the family royal.</l><l>The same that Cherokee history adorn,</l><l>Were not assumed, but were  proudly borne,</l><l>By descendants of these old English sires,</l><l>Who safety sought at the Cherokee camp fires.</l><l>The name Tahlequah to this town was given</l><l>By the old Cherokees, when they were driven</l><l>From their eastern homes, afar to the west,</l><l>Till they reached this dear spot, "A haven of rest,"</l><l>Poor, sorrowing exiles, of their homes bereft</l><l>Grieving for the fire-sides which they had left.</l><l>God who takes care of those whom the strong oppress,</l><l>And pities them in their sore distress</l><l>Brought it to pass, that the land of the given,</l><l>By treaty as sacred and solemn as Heaven</l><l>Was better than that of which they had been despoiled,</l><l>Little the white brothers knew of this land</l><l>Which they gave to the remnant of this proud band.</l><l>Knew naught of the mineral wealth which hides</l><l>Its bounteous stores in the mountain sides;</l><l>Naught of the verdant fruitful plants,</l><l>Nor the varied resources this country contains.</l><l>Here the Cherokee rested, their long journey o'er,</l><l>And this wildwood was given to be theirs evermore,</l><l>Here they made the council-ground.</l><l>And here their Kihegas oft were found</l><l>In solemn assembly and council grave;</l><l>When laws to govern the nation they gave,</l><l>Here, Sequoyah, the Cadmus, his alpabet [sic] brought,</l><l>Whcih [sic] with infinite patience and skill he wrought,</l><l>Schools were established to teach the youth</l><l>And churches, to spread Christainity's [sic] truth.</l><l>Soon the wilderness was made to bloom</l><l>As homes were bulit [sic] dispelled its gloom.</l><l>And the town by the little woodland stream</l><l>Threw its light afar, like a diamond's gleam.</l><l>Such was the birth of this historic town,</l><l>Which for her beauty is of wide renown,</l><l>For her fountains that gush from the rough hillside,</l><l>And her halls of learning, the Nation's pride.</l><l>Like Athens of old, she is of learning the seat,</l><l>So peaceful and quiet, a sylvan retreat.</l></lg><note anchored="true" type="inline"><p xml:id="adair_1305"> Kihegas-Leading men </p></note></div></body></text></TEI>