<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lkr_confederacy_13011"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Spirit of the Confederacy</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Rogers, Loula Kendall, 1838-1931</reg><orig>Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Beck Center</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>10k</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability><p xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1301">2008 Emory University. Permission is granted to

download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>2008</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/17ctz</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Rogers, Loula Kendall, "The Spirit of the Confederacy" Loula

	   Kendall Rogers Papers, 1854-1930. Manuscript and Rare Books

	   Library, Emory University</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1302">This digital text is produced from the Loula Kendall

	   Rogers Papers, generously loaned to the Beck Center by    	

The Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library at Emory University.  The production of this digital text was undertaken by the Beck Center for the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Early 20th Century Literature</rs><rs type="language">American</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs><rs type="form">Unedited</rs><rs type="genre">Poetry</rs><rs type="geography">United States</rs><date>1800-1899</date><date>1900-1999</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list><item>Civil War, U.S., 1861-1865--Poetry</item><item>Confederate States of America.</item><item>Women authors, American--19th Century</item><item>Women authors, American--20th Century</item><item>United Daughters of the Confederacy.</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>2008</date><label>Woodruff Graduate Fellow</label><name>Stewart Varner</name>XML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="lkr_confederacy_13010"><body xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1306"><pb facs="lkr_confederacy001" xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1303" n="[1]"/><div xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1305" type="poem"><head><seg type="short-title">THE SPIRIT OF THE CONFEDERACY</seg></head><head type="sub">"Unveils a Picture Of Morn and Night,<lb/>

      Yet sweeps the lingering mists away!"</head><byline rend="center">By Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers<lb/>

      Poet Laureate Of United Daughters Of The Confederacy<lb/>

      Georgia Division.</byline><lg type="stanza"><l>'Tis Morn in the Southland.  Upon each hill,</l><l>There gleams a tint of gold, and in the vale afar</l><l>Resounds the merry call of one who keeps</l><l>The wandering lamb from straying o'er snowy field</l><l>To vie with each whose store shall weigh the most,</l><l>Or who at eve shall bring the <hi rend="underline">finest</hi> yield?</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Peace, Holy Peace rests on the Plantation Home,</l><l>From teeming Orchard to the Garden Gate,</l><l>The sun-lit heights of "Georgia's Old Red Hills"</l><l>Bespeak the calm that rests upon each State.</l><l>King Cotton proudly smiles upon his royal seat,</l><l>While Autumn fruits their countless joys displayed,</l><l>And golden grain breathes life and health complete</l><l>For Heaven's touch on every spot is laid!</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>The Light of Holy Writ beams on the sacred hearth,</l><l>No prowling Bandit there!  No evil soul to roam,</l><l>The Master Mistress, Child and good old Mammy knelt,</l><l>To thank the Lord for peace in a Christian Home.</l><l>Our own dear land!  Our hallowed Southland Home!</l><l>Was there ever another spot like thee?</l><l>Where dependant friends (<hi rend="underline">not </hi><hi rend="underline">slaves</hi>) who with life's last breath,</l><l>Despite the War, could true and faithful be?</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>And was there ever a Christmas Time so glad?</l><l>With Banjo, Violin, Song and Dance that filled </l><l>The heart with joy over-flowing and merriment unrestrained</l><l>In honor of the family whose wealth they helped to build?</l><l>But list to that destructive March o'er Georgia's peaceful soil</l><l>Tramping over human hears they hasten to the grave.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>'Tis Night!  Darksome Night!  No star illume the way.</l><l>Then Statesmen soon on terms of Peace, three different times were sent</l><l>But not received!  For other views prevailed</l><l>Against all sovereign rights of State Coercion as intent.</l><l>Then, the Spirit of 76 illumined all the South,</l><l>And steel met steel alike with American zeal anew,</l><l>Till "The Stars and Bars" at Manassas brought forth a ray of light,</l><l>And proved to all the spirit which King's Mountain found so true!</l></lg><pb facs="lkr_confederacy002" xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1304" n="[2]"/><lg type="stanza"><l>All Battles were unwelcome - but homes in ashes laid</l><l>Brought forth in words immortal emblazed upon the air</l><l>An urge unto the spirit, in light that cannot fade,</l><l>This slogan of the Daughters - "<hi rend="underline">Live</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Love</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Think</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Pray</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Dare</hi>!"</l><l>Then the Holy Spirit guided - and compensation came</l><l>When Davis, Lee, and Stonewall add Righteousness to Fame,</l><l>And 'neath Heaven's Light inspired still forward moved the Gray</l><l>E'en though their number lessened mid storm-clouds all the way.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>So 'twas the Faith of our Fathers that gave courage to the true,</l><l>And it led by God's own Spirit all our Southern Soldiers through</l><l>Not a soldier of the Southland under General Lee's command</l><l>Would rob one of his property, or flash the fire brand.</l><l>And to all who served their Country in Justice and in Right</l><l>May Daughters of the Confederacy the Gates of Love unbar</l><l>And lead the Blue and Gray as friends to Heaven's Crowning Star!</l></lg></div></body><back xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1309"><pb facs="lkr_confederacy003" xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1307" n="[3]"/><div xml:id="lkr_confederacy_2" type="authors_note"><p xml:id="lkr_confederacy_1308">Spirit of the Confederacy</p></div></back></text></TEI>