<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lkr_gallant_13010"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Gallant Old Boys in Gray</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Rogers, Loula Kendall, 1838-1931</reg><orig>Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Beck Center</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>10k</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability><p xml:id="lkr_gallant_1301">2008 Emory University. Permission is granted to

download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>2008</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/17cxc</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Rogers, Loula Kendall, "The Gallant Old Boys in Gray" Loula

	   Kendall Rogers Papers, 1854-1930. Manuscript and Rare Books

	   Library, Emory University</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="lkr_gallant_1302">This digital text is produced from the Loula Kendall

	   Rogers Papers, generously loaned to the Beck Center by    	

The Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library at Emory University.  The production of this digital text was undertaken by the Beck Center for the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Early 20th Century Literature</rs><rs type="language">American</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs><rs type="form">Unedited</rs><rs type="genre">Poetry</rs><rs type="geography">United States</rs><date>1800-1899</date><date>1900-1999</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list><item>Women poets, American--Georgia.</item><item>Women authors, American--19th Century</item><item>Women authors, American--20th Century</item><item>Civil War, U.S., 1861-1865--Poetry</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>2008</date><label>Woodruff Graduate Fellow</label><name>Stewart Varner</name>XML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="lkr_gallant_1309"><body xml:id="lkr_gallant_1305"><pb facs="lkr_gallant001" xml:id="lkr_gallant_1303" n="[1]"/><div xml:id="lkr_gallant_1304" type="poem"><head>The Gallant<lb/>

      Old Boys in Gray</head><lg type="stanza"><l>They are marching today in their armor of gray,</l><l rend="indent">Where proudly in youth they so gallantly trod,</l><l>E're Sherman invaded in battle array</l><l rend="indent">And swore each "Rebel should sleep in the sod."</l><l>But the strife and such boasting are all cast aside,</l><l>As they glance on their banner with joy and with pride</l><l>Still beaming with Justice and Mercy and Right,</l><l>For it waved o'er Lee in heaven's own light!</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>No cause that is just and guarded with trust</l><l rend="indent">Can ever be lost to a patriot soul,</l><l>Nor the rights of a state be  trampled in dust</l><l rend="indent">When honorable valor leads on to the goal.</l><l>Then bravely look upward with conscience unstained</l><l>By reckless disorder, or vice unrestrained,</l><l>For you won that glory which never shall fade</l><l>It's pure as thy banner, thy musket and blade.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Four wars have displayed of what  metal they're made,</l><l rend="indent">Old Guilford, Monterey and Manassas proclaim,</l><l>Then Spain with her heraldry, her pomp and her power</l><l rend="indent">Eclipsed as Hobson won honor and fame.</l><l>This God-given spirit came down to the son</l><l>When Germans retreated and Victory won;</l><l>Then cheer upon cheer for our Veterans in Gray</l><l>Who honor both flags of America today!</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>All hail to Atlanta! Queen city of light!</l><l rend="indent">Whose ministering love gives welcome and rest</l><l>To all who battle for justice and right,</l><l rend="indent">From the north and the south, the east and west.</l><l>Encamped on her soil, by thousands they came</l><l>And Gordon won chaplets and crosses of fame,</l><l>Who are welcomed today with peans so gay,</l><l>And deem it an honor to march with the Gray!</l></lg><byline>LOULA KENDALL ROGERS.</byline></div></body><back xml:id="lkr_gallant_1308"><div xml:id="lkr_gallant_002" type="note"><p xml:id="lkr_gallant_1306">Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers, of Tennille, author of the above, was a "girl of the sixties" and is the widow of a splendid Confederate soldier, a captain in the Third Georgia regiment.  Her son, too, followed his soldier father's example and remains overseas.</p><p xml:id="lkr_gallant_1307">Mrs. H.M Franklin, president of the Georgia division U.D.C. is

      the only daughter of Mrs. Rogers.</p></div></back></text></TEI>