<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lkr_absent_1307"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To My Absent Husband</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Rogers, Loula Kendall, 1838-1931</reg><orig>Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Beck Center</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>6k</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability><p xml:id="lkr_absent_1301">2008 Emory University. Permission is granted to

download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>2008</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/17cqj</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Rogers, Loula Kendall, "To My Absent Husband" Loula

	   Kendall Rogers Papers, 1854-1930. Manuscript and Rare Books

	   Library, Emory University</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="lkr_absent_1302">This digital text is produced from the Loula Kendall

	   Rogers Papers, generously loaned to the Beck Center by    	

The Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library at Emory University.  The production of this digital text was undertaken by the Beck Center for the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Early 20th Century Literature</rs><rs type="language">American</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs><rs type="form">Unedited</rs><rs type="genre">Poetry</rs><rs type="geography">United States</rs><date>1800-1899</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list><item>Marriage--United States--19th Century.</item><item>Civil War, U.S., 1861-1865--Poetry</item><item>American poetry--19th century.</item><item>Women authors, American--19th Century</item><item>Women authors, American--20th Century</item><item>War.</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>2008</date><label>Woodruff Graduate Fellow</label><name>Stewart Varner</name>XML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="lkr_absent_1306"><body xml:id="lkr_absent_1305"><pb facs="lkr_absent001" xml:id="lkr_absent_1303" n="[1]"/><div xml:id="lkr_absent_1304"><head rend="center">(FOR THE SOUTHERN CONFEDERACY)<lb/><seg type="short-title">TO MY ABSENT HUSBAND</seg></head><lg type="stanza"><l>Thou'rt gone!  Thou'rt gone! no more may I hear</l><l>Love's lingering tones lowly breathed in my ear.</l><l>My bower is desolate where lately there shone</l><l>A bright beaming star - but now I'm alone.</l><l>'Tis beautiful there, more brilliant the flowers</l><l>Of autumn than those of the past summer hours,</l><l>Sweet birds too are singing, but I hear not their lay</l><l>My spirit is lonely for thou art away.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Each favorite haunt tells me, dearest of thee,</l><l>On my heart is thine image where'er I may be;</l><l>When I call to the echo no sound is so sweet</l><l>As the name of all others I'd rather repeat;</l><l>But thy country has called thee, in her hour of need,</l><l>While the groans of her dying for victory plead,</l><l>And I know that thy valor  in her service will shine</l><l>Though thy strength may be feeble, her glory is thine!</l><l>God shield thee in suffering, and keep thee from harm</l><l>In peace or in battle, in sunlight or storm,</l><l>And memory, sweet memory illumine thy heart</l><l>With dreams of our past that ne'er may depart.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Thou'rt away!  Thou'rt away, where the cannon's loud roar</l><l>Sends terror to thousands who'll hear it no more;</l><l>There war wildly rages and dangers beset,</l><l>Yet thy home and thy loved one thou'lt never forget.</l><l>I gazed on thy form as it passed from my sight,</l><l>Thine cager war charger exulting in might,</l><l>And called in my anguish on the God of the free,</l><l>Believing He'd watch o'er my brothers and thee.</l><l>Each morning and evening our prayers will unite,</l><l>That he may defend us in justice and right,</l><l>Give us liberty and triumph with gladness again,</l><l>And no more let battle cries sound o'er the plain.</l></lg><byline><name type="person"><choice><reg>Rogers, Loula Kendall</reg><orig>LEOLA</orig></choice></name></byline></div></body></text></TEI>