<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lkr_southland_1307"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Spirit of the Southland</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Rogers, Loula Kendall, 1838-1931</reg><orig>Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Beck Center</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>10k</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability><p xml:id="lkr_southland_1301">2008 Emory University. Permission is granted to

download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>2008</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/17dgp</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Rogers, Loula Kendall, "The Spirit of the

	    Southland," <date>17 February 1927</date>. Loula

	   Kendall Rogers Papers, 1854-1930. Manuscript and Rare Books

	   Library, Emory University</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="lkr_southland_1302">This digital text is produced from the Loula Kendall

	   Rogers Papers, generously loaned to the Beck Center by    	

The Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library at Emory University.  The production of this digital text was undertaken by the Beck Center for the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Early 20th Century Literature</rs><rs type="language">American</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs><rs type="form">Unedited</rs><rs type="genre">Poetry</rs><rs type="geography">United States</rs><date>1900-1999</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list><item>United Daughters of the Confederacy.</item><item>Women authors, American--19th Century</item><item>Women authors, American--20th Century</item><item>United States, Southern</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>2008</date><label>Woodruff Graduate Fellow</label><name>Stewart Varner</name>XML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="lkr_southland_1306"><body xml:id="lkr_southland_1305"><pb facs="lkr_southland001" xml:id="lkr_southland_1303" n="[1]"/><div xml:id="lkr_southland_1304" type="poem"><dateline>BARNESVILLE NEWS-GAZETTE, THURSDAY, FEBRUARY 17, 1927.</dateline><head><seg type="short-title">THE SPIRIT OF THE SOUTHLAND</seg><lb/></head><head type="sub">Unveils a Picture Of Morn and Night,<lb/>

      Yet sweeps the lingering mists away!</head><byline>By Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers, Poet Laureate,<lb/>

      Georgia Division U.D.C.</byline><dateline>Read during the 32nd Convention of Daughters of the Confed-<lb/>

      eracy at Statesboro, Georgia, On <date when="1926-10-27">

         October 27th, 1926</date>.</dateline><lg type="stanza"><l>'Tis Morn, radiant Morn!  Upon each hill</l><l>There gleams a tint of gold, and in the vale afar</l><l>Is heard the merry call of one who keeps</l><l>Each wandering lamb from straying o'er the bar.</l><l>The ploughman sings a cheer to new born day</l><l>And maids light-hearted roam o'er snowy field</l><l>Or who at eve should bring the finest yield?</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Peace, lovely Peace, rests upon the Plantation Home!</l><l>From teeming orchard to the garden gate,</l><l>The sun-lit heights of Georgia's old red hills</l><l>Bespeak the calm that dwells upon each State.</l><l>King Cotton proudly smiles upon his royal seat,</l><l>As autumn fruits their countless joys displayed;</l><l>And golden grain breathes life and health complete,</l><l>For Heaven's touch on every scene is laid!</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>The Light of Holy Love beams o'er the peaceful hearth, for</l><l><hi rend="underline">There was no Bandit then</hi>!  No evil soul to roam,</l><l>The Master, Mistress, and loved old Mammy knelt,</l><l>To thank the Heavenly Father for their blessed Christian Home,</l><l>Our own dear land!  Our hallowed Southern Home!</l><l>Was there ever on Earth a land surpassing thee?</l><l>Where friends dependant (not slaves) who with their <sic>lates</sic> breath</l><l>Despite all war, could true and faithful be?</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>And was there ever a Christmas Time so glad?</l><l>With Banjo, Violin, Dance and Joy that filled </l><l>The heart with happiness pure and unrestrained </l><l>In knowing those whose wealth they help to build?</l><l>But list!  Far down yon vale the thundering guns of war</l><l>Break up the placid flow of Atlantic wave,</l><l>And wildly rush o'er loving peaceful homes</l><l>TO cast their blooming roses in the grave! </l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>'Tis Night!  Cheerless Night!  No star illumes the way.</l><l>Our statesmen wise <hi rend="underline">on terms of peace </hi>were sent</l><l><hi rend="underline">But not received</hi>.  Far different views prevailed -</l><l><hi rend="underline">Against all Sovereign Rights coercion was intent!</hi></l><l>Then the Spirit of 1776 reawakened o'er the hills</l><l>And steel alike met steel with American valor anew,</l><l>Till "The Stars and Bars" at Manassas brought forth a hopeful light,</l><l>And proved to all, the bravery of King's Mountain still is

	true!</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Through strife was long avoided, yet our homes in ashes laid</l><l>Brought in the mystic ruins words emblazed upon the air</l><l>Soul cheering to the spirit with a light that cannot fade,</l><l>This slogan of the Daughters - Live, Love, Think, Pray, Dare!</l><l>The Holy Spirit guided, and compensation came</l><l>When Davis, Lee, and Stonewall add Righteousness to Fame,</l><l>And with Heaven's light inspired still onward marched the Gray</l><l>Though their number lessened daily mid the war clouds on the way.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>'Twas the <hi rend="underline">Faith of our Fathers</hi>, which gave <hi rend="underline">courage to the true,</hi></l><l>And it led by Holy Spirit all of our Southern Soldiers through</l><l>Not a hero of the Southland under General Lee's command</l><l>Would rob one of their property, or flash the fire brand!</l><l>Then Hail, all Hail, with loving cheer, the memory tonight</l><l>Of all who served their country in Justice and in Right,</l><l>And may Daughters of Confederacy the gates of love unbar</l><l>And lead the Blue and Gray as friends to Heaven's Crowning Star!</l></lg></div></body></text></TEI>