<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lkr_tribute_13013"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Tribute of Love</title><author><name type="person"><choice><reg>Rogers, Loula Kendall, 1838-1931</reg><orig>Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers</orig></choice></name></author><respStmt><resp>Compiled and edited by</resp><name>Beck Center</name><name/></respStmt></titleStmt><extent>10k</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address><availability><p xml:id="lkr_tribute_1301">2008 Emory University. Permission is granted to

download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact either: Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p></availability><date>2008</date><idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/17djz</idno></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Emory Women Writers Resource Project</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Rogers, Loula Kendall, "A Tribute of Love," <date>20

	    October 1928</date>. Loula

	   Kendall Rogers Papers, 1854-1930. Manuscript and Rare Books

	   Library, Emory University</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p xml:id="lkr_tribute_1302">This digital text is produced from the Loula Kendall

	   Rogers Papers, generously loaned to the Beck Center by    	

The Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library at Emory University.  The production of this digital text was undertaken by the Beck Center for the Emory Women Writers Resource Project.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="lcsh"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation><rs type="collection">Early 20th Century Literature</rs><rs type="language">American</rs><rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs><rs type="form">Unedited</rs><rs type="genre">Poetry</rs><rs type="geography">United States</rs><date>1900-1999</date></creation><textClass><keywords scheme="#lcsh"><list><item>United Daughters of the Confederacy.</item><item>Women authors, American--19th Century</item><item>Women authors, American--20th Century</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change><date>2008</date><label>Woodruff Graduate Fellow</label><name>Stewart Varner</name>XML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:id="lkr_tribute_13012"><body xml:id="lkr_tribute_1306"><pb facs="lkr_tribute001" xml:id="lkr_tribute_1303" n="1"/><div xml:id="lkr_tribute_1305" type="poem"><head><seg type="short-title">A Tribute Of Love</seg></head><head type="sub">To The Memory Of Miss Mildred Lewis Rutherford<lb/>

      State and General Historian, From The United Daughters<lb/> 

      Of The Confederacy.</head><byline>By The Poet Laureate Mrs Loula Kendall Rogers.</byline><lg type="stanza"><l>When all the world is beaming bright oftimes there comes a cloud,</l><l>And Nature droops in sympathy as the giant Oak is bowed,</l><l>When a favorite flower gently pleads as if in search of aid,</l><l>O tell me is there a land where Roses never fade?</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>There is a land, a radiant Land, of one Eternal Day,</l><l>No night is there, no storm of War to dim its golden ray,</l><l>The thunder's roar, the battle shout, terrific war whoops cease,</l><l>And all the universe repeats a song of Love and Peace.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Our Georgia Rose transfigured, finds congenial friends anew,</l><l>Her snow white purity acclaimed by all the great and true,</l><l>The King of Kings has placed a Crown upon her brow so fair</l><l>Then sorrow not -  but Oh, rejoice!  For her reward is there!</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Her service here was knowledge - transforming youthful mind</l><l>Uplifting Lucy Cobb with her learning most divine,</l><l>Then when the day was over and stars illume the night,</l><l>She was planning still for Georgia, and new ways to make it bright.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Oh, who in all the world but she had ever penned a thought,</l><l>On great Historic Records which her native State had wrought?</l><l>Of the First Atlantic Steamer that ever sailed beneath the sun,</l><l>Was surely manned in Georgia!  And Georgia surely won!</l></lg><pb facs="lkr_tribute002" xml:id="lkr_tribute_1304" n="2"/><lg type="stanza"><l>She then upheld the veiling where all the Southland leads</l><l>In Cotton Gins, and Missions where the Orphan sadly pleads,</l><l>And where the South was <hi rend="underline">first</hi> to grace the Presidential Chair,</l><l>For Washington our leader, was a well known Hero there.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Her Truths of History are well known and prove without a doubt,</l><l>If blame was laid upon the South, she always brought it out,</l><l>For Sovereignty, the Rights of State, her heart was ever true</l><l>Her path was always blessed with Truth and Honor's unfailing glue.</l></lg><lg type="stanza"><l>Then let us follow the gleam she leaves, high up on land and sea,</l><l>The Faith and Honor of noble aims for our glorious U.D.C.</l><l>And when the day beams fade away, may angles waft above</l><l>The songs with which we greet her soul in Everlasting Love!</l></lg><dateline>Tennille, Georgia<lb/>

      October 20, 1928</dateline></div></body><back xml:id="lkr_tribute_13011"><pb facs="lkr_tribute" xml:id="lkr_tribute_1307" n="[3]"/><div xml:id="lkr_tribute_2" type="authors_note"><p xml:id="lkr_tribute_1308">For 34<hi rend="super">th</hi> Convention<lb/>

      Please return these two . as I have no<lb/>

      other copies</p><p xml:id="lkr_tribute_1309">L.K. Rogers</p><p xml:id="lkr_tribute_13010">memorial of Miss Mildred</p></div></back></text></TEI>